<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A gagge for the Pope, and the Iesuits: or The arraignement, and execution of Antichrist Shevving plainely, that Antichrist shall be discouered, and punished in this vvorld: to the amasement of all obstinate papists.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120961</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856152</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1252:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A gagge for the Pope, and the Iesuits: or The arraignement, and execution of Antichrist Shevving plainely, that Antichrist shall be discouered, and punished in this vvorld: to the amasement of all obstinate papists.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Edward Blackmore, and are to be sould at his shop, at the great south-dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GAGGE FOR THE POPE, AND THE IESVITS: <hi>OR</hi> THE ARRAIGNEMENT, AND EXECVTION OF ANTICHRIST.</p>
            <p>Shevving plainely, that Antichriſt ſhall be diſcouered, and puniſhed in this VVorld: <hi>to the amaſement of all obſtinate</hi> PAPISTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop, at the Great South-dore of <hi>Paules.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:21678:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Lucan. lib. 7. Pharſal.</bibl> 
               <hi>Hoe placet, ô ſuperi, cum vobis vertere cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta propoſitum, noſtris erroribus addere crimen?</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21678:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE; VVILLIAM: EARLE of PENBROOK, Lord Chamberlaine to his Maieſties <hi>Houſhold, and one of his moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Councell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I intend nothing by this Diſcourſe, but the glory of God, the good of my Country, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of <hi>Princes,</hi> and the ſeaſoning of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: ſo doe I propoſe no man fitter to Patroniſe the ſame, then
<pb facs="tcp:21678:3"/> your ſelfe, ſprung from ſo illuſtrious a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our moderne Stories reioyce againe in the illuſtration of the name and actions of <hi>Herbert:</hi> but aboue all, my motiues ariſe from your Noble diſpoſition toward <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> glory, and pious zeale to propagate the cauſe of Religion, which at this day is ſet vpon by viperous calumniation, as if either God meant not to performe his promiſe, concerning the ſtripping the <hi>Strumpet</hi> naked, <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 3.</note> who hath made drunke the Kings of the earth with the cup of abomination: or <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie</hi> determined, like <hi>Prometheus</hi> his <hi>Vulture,</hi> to feed vpon the heart of Religion, and eat out the bowels of ſanctitie, and truth But O thou God of heauen, thou laugheſt the <note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> deuiſes of men to ſcorne, and wilt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy owne cauſe in deſpight of <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi> and <hi>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee Princes</hi> of the earth, looke yee <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 12.</note> kiſſe the ſonne, leaſt he be angry, and yee periſh in the Way, when his wrath ſhall ſuddenly burne.</p>
            <p>Wherefore great <hi>Lord,</hi> made ſo much the greater by all the <hi>Concomitants</hi> of <hi>Noble birth,</hi> and remarkeable deſeruing, accept I pray you of this poore <hi>Tractate,</hi> wherein though
<pb facs="tcp:21678:3"/> I come ſtrangely toward you with a dutie from an vnknowne name, and vnfortunate man, as we prophanely abuſe the <hi>Character,</hi> yet with ſo good a heart, that in regard of the cauſe, which is Gods, and your ſelfe, who haue anſwered reputation with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, I am cheerfully animated to wade out of this ſtreame, by the ſupportation of ſo noble an arme, which can keep me from ſinking, though there were ſome whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole to fall into.</p>
            <p>As for aſperſion of preſumption, ſtepping out of my own Circle, medling with tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent matters, tenuity of wit, or deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of knowledge, I wipe all away with a Principle in <hi>Euripid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.—Nullus ſibi ſimilis in peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iphigenia in Tauris.</note> 
               <hi>homo, quoties ad audaciam ex metu venerit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But indeed what ſhould I be affrighted with the <hi>Popes</hi> fulmination, or curſes, <hi>Lucan</hi> anſwers;
<q>
                  <hi>Tollite ſignaduces, fatorum impellite curſum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 5. Pharſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpem veſtram preſtate diis, fortuna<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tantos det vobis animos, quantos fugientibus hoſtem cauſa dabat.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The blaſtings of opinion, or windy cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21678:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Impia laetatur vulgatae nomine famae,—Theſſaliis.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The diſpleaſure or contracted brow of a Prince? <hi>No, no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſaris aduentu tuta gladiator arena,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 6. de Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>exit, &amp; auxilium non leue vultus habet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The imputations of iudicious men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Simplex oratio veritatis eſt;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> variarum habet vtrin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> interpretationum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eurip. Phaeniſſae.</note> 
               <hi>habet enim ipſa congruentiam, ſed iniquus ſermo aegrotans in ſeipſum, medicamimum habet opus ſapientiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſertion of friends? who be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amicos in rebus aduerſis conuenit amicis adeſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eurip. Oreſtes.</note> 
               <hi>Nam cum Deus faelicitatem dederit, Quid opus est amicis? Sufficit ipſe Deus prodeſſe volens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, ſo I haue your fauour and my owne ends, I am ſtartled at nothing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency in ſo great aduenture, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines to put polluted handes into the waters of life: which as I hope the God of heauen will pardon, becauſe of my honeſt deſires to magnifie his greatnes: ſo your Honor will graciouſly admit, becauſe of my willing heart to exemplifie your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21678:4"/>
            <head>THE ARRAIGNEMENT AND EXECVTION OF ANTICHRIST.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Would faine act my owne Scean, and with a modeſt zeale enter into a Diſcourſe, that ſhall ſhow you the hand of God writing on the wall, more fearefull and terrible to hard-hearted <hi>Papiſts,</hi> then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Belſhazzers</hi> fatall night to <note place="margin">Daniel. 5.</note> himſelfe and his people. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you then, if you can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crectly auoyd, or charitably confute ignorant <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and penurious Newes-mongers, vnderſtand, what I purpoſe in my following Treatiſe; meerely to ſhow you, that theſe troubles of <hi>Europe,</hi> be but the beginnings of <hi>Romes</hi> deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Beaſt with ſeauen heads and ten hornes muſt <note place="margin">Apoc. 12</note> be diſcouered, as ſhe walloweth in the den of abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and filthineſſe of corruption; after which ſhe ſhall be rowſed and hunted out of breath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aken and laſhed with ſtripes, bound and ſtripped of her pompe, and at laſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and conſumed with fire: which although it may haue relation to the euerlaſting horror of hell, yet in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of learned Diuines, muſt be explicated by ſome effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall humiliation on earth. Wherin if repentance remorſe, and compunction of ſpirit, cannot frame the maſter peece of Conuerſion, the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> ſhall be wrought by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21678:5"/> of a ſtronger arme, and that from a ſecular Prince. And if in this the <hi>Emperours</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> or other potent Kings haue fayled, as too-too baſely proſtrating themſelues to the power of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> no queſtion God will puniſh them for vnder-valuing his glory, or diuiding and partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating that greatnes, which he hath giuen to euery King intire in his owne Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Now that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath, vnder ſanctified titles, both abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Religion, and deceiued the world, and that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt ſuch pride, blaſphemy, and hypocriſie; yea, offended with ſuch <hi>Princes,</hi> as ſtill adore the Beaſt, is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by many relations: Eſpecially a large Letter written, and printed long ſince in the Spaniſh tongue to King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the ſecond, in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> wherein is not onely the Genealogie of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> but a delicate Picture of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and his <hi>Cardinals,</hi> kneeling before the Deuill, ſitting in a chayre of <hi>State,</hi> who deliuers him an <hi>Indenture,</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> with many ſeales, allowing him to be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſo to execute his authoritie: this was compoſed by one <hi>Alonſo de Penna Fuertes,</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> and out of this, with many other <hi>Claſſick</hi> Authors, this <hi>Enchiridion</hi> is extracted, and I hope to make all I proiect apparant, as farre as man may coniecture, or fals to my poore proportion of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Method</hi> then, which I would obſerue, ariſeth from the 1. <hi>Diſcouery, 2. Arraignement, 3. and execution of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> In the diſcouery you ſhall haue ſome obſeruations taken from, 1. effectuall contingents, 2. and probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures. In the Arraignement the indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ements are framed, 1. from contradicting the word of God, 2. from diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the truth with falſe doctrines, 3. and from abuſing the people with lying miracles. In the ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and execution, the <hi>Bonarges</hi> is deliuered, 1. from the mouth of God, 2. the predictions of <hi>Sybels,</hi> 3. the inuectiues of their owne canonized Fathers, 4. and reuelations of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Women; of all which in order, or as orderly as I can.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21678:5"/>
                  <head>The diſcouery of Antichriſt.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the diſcouery of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> how euer I need goe no further then <hi>Daniels</hi> weekes and times, or his foure beaſts, <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſions, the Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>Reuelation</hi> of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and thoſe wonderfull Expoſitions of learned men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſubiect in hand: yet you ſhall haue other obſervations, namely, that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the yeere 1666. a time wherin the glory of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1666</label> muſt be ecclipſed, or at leaſt ſo darkened, that it ſhall neuer ſhine with outward glory, nor eminent maieſty: many haue ſet downe, that the numerall letters of all <hi>Alphabets</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to this number, and denotate the ſame, as if it were a thing purpoſed from the beginning, and like a <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gliphicke,</hi> repreſenting the name, and marke of the Beaſt in the <hi>Apocalyps:</hi> for example, <hi>c.</hi> ſignifies a 100, <hi>d.</hi> 500. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alphab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ts</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merall letters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>i.</hi> one, <hi>l. 50. m.</hi> a 1000. <hi>v.</hi> fiue, and <hi>x.</hi> 10. all which ſummed together make a 1666. Others out of the name of <hi>Paulus vice Deus,</hi> borrowing a little libertie to make the firſt <hi>v</hi> a double, collect the ſame number from <hi>l. v. v. i. c. d. v.</hi> which Letters likewiſe amount to 666. Others take the name of the Beaſt out of <hi>Papa Vicarius Dei generalis in terris,</hi> where there are ſix <hi>Vnites,</hi> two <hi>v.</hi> which make 10. <hi>l. 50. c.</hi> a 100. and <hi>d.</hi> 500. all which amount to 666. Others deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant vpon the triple Crowne of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſome other tearmes more ſignificant, as in all the learned Expoſitors of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation</hi> is apparant. Laſt of all they haue played with the very <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Papa,</hi> as if there were a myſtery in the <note place="margin">Papa.</note> Letters, and that <hi>Papa</hi> did ſignifie <hi>Poculum aurcum plenum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> abominationis,</hi> the golden cup full of abomination: and ſuch is the will of God, that as <hi>Ahabs</hi> little Cloud increaſed to a great ſtorme, ſo out of theſe triuiall animaduerſions, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter might be gathered for the diſcouery of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> Prelacy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21678:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Effectuall Contingents.</hi> Proteſtants.</head>
                  <p>NOw let vs come forward to <hi>Effectuall Contingents,</hi> which are apparant from the progreſſion of the Goſpell in all the Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments of <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelues in their owne Papiſticall <hi>Prouinces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt then concerning Religion, now called <hi>Reformed,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Proteſtants.</note> who knowes not, what <hi>England, Scotland, Denmarke, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Sweden,</hi> the <hi>low Countries,</hi> and many great townes and Provinces, both in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France</hi> haue done? and that with reſolution neuer to returne to the vomit againe? Who ſees not the proſperitie of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and the reſt, who for Religions ſake, and to oppoſe that monſtrous <hi>Hydra,</hi> the Inquiſition, diſplayed by the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a,</hi> haue euer ſince maintained ſuch Warres, that the world is at a gaze at their Protector? Who confeſſeth not, what <hi>France</hi> bringeth forth, ſuch Proteſtant Armies, ſuch defenſiue townes, that their faith is as ſtrong as their walls, ſuch glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous troopes, worthy Congregations, zealous miniſters, and religious people, that for all the <hi>State</hi> allowes them not publicke exerciſe of Religion, yet ſuch is their eſtate, that many thouſands are reſolued to maintaine the cauſe of the Goſpell? Who vnderſtands not, how <hi>Switzerland</hi> is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and for the moſt part affected to the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Whoſe heart doth not leape for ioy (eſpecially if his name be written in the booke of life) to apprehend, how the ſpacious <hi>Germany</hi> hath her ſeuerall <hi>Proteſtant Prouinces,</hi> and reformed Citties, how-euer the <hi>Popes</hi> aduocates miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tearme them <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Hereticks? O Geneua, Geneua,</hi> I bleſſe thy name for bleſſing the God of all bleſſing, who hath waſhed thee cleane from the filthineſſe of ſuperſtition, and thou haſt kept thy white garments vnſpotted, yea by demonſtration ſhewed plainely, that the wings of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubines</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21678:6"/> haue ouer-ſhadowed thee. Shall I bring into this number the <hi>Prouinces</hi> of <hi>Auſtria, Stiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Carmola, Carinthia,</hi> why the Emperor himſelfe knowes, they are moſt of them <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and within three myle of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna,</hi> Engliſhmen haue ſeene fiftie Caroſſes at a Proteſtant Sermon, yea, they haue told the Fryers within the walles to their faces, that they would do as the men of <hi>Berea</hi> did, examine their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine by the Word of God. As for the terrible affrightings of hoſtilitie, whereby the countenances of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and other Prouinces are euen ſadded againe, and ſeeme bloodles with impietie of ſoule, to thinke vpon their ruines and deuaſtation, although the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> runne vp and downe with the <hi>Popes</hi> fulmination in their mouthes, fire and ſword in their handes, malice and revenge in their hearts, death and deſtruction in their actions; and that the voice of <hi>Rachel</hi> is euery where heard mourning for her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <note place="margin">Iere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</note> yet are there thouſandes that haue not bowed their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> and are humbled with <hi>Iob</hi> to cry out, though <note place="margin">King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Iob.</note> thou kill me, I will not forſake thee: and could all this be done without the ſpeciall providence of God, and his all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearching eye, that will at laſt diſcouer the pollution of this <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> den, and the deceit of the <hi>Strumpet?</hi> anſwere a Gods name, you that muſt anſwer before the Iudgement throne of the Lambe, how comes this about, if the <hi>Papac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſhall not come to ruine? and thus much for the <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Papiſts.</head>
                  <p>COncerning <hi>Papiſts,</hi> how many <hi>Statutes</hi> in <hi>France, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Papiſts</note> and other places, haue beene enacted diuers hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres ſince, againſt the pride, aua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice, and vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sea of <hi>Rome?</hi> What paſquils and inuectiues haue beene ſet vp euen in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe? traducing the <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Cardinalls</hi> for their vicious liues, and abominable impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tie? What outrages haue beene committed to the ſacking of <hi>Rome,</hi> and irreligious prophanation of ſuch things, as were reputed ſacred, and all this by <hi>Catholick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Souldiers? What
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21678:7"/> diſcontentments beganne betweene <hi>Philip</hi> the 2. of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> not long after the death of <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, when the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> in his Maſters behalfe exprobra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Conclaue</hi> of <hi>Cardinals,</hi> for proclaiming the King an enemy to the Church, that a man would wonder how he was afterward diuerted to bend his forces againſt them in the low Countries? How often haue the <hi>Grandes</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> repined at the welath and ambition of the Clergie? With what fearefull out cryes haue the people murmured at the tyranny of the <hi>Inquiſition?</hi> Are not the Fryers at this inſtant I meane the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans</hi> at variance about the originall ſinne of the Virgin <hi>Mary?</hi> Did not <hi>Sauoy</hi> a while agoe proteſt againſt the tenths of the Church, and beganne to ſtartle at ſome peremptory proceedings of the Clergie? Was not <hi>Venice</hi> reſolued to moderate the bountie of men defunct, who enfeoffed the Church with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary donatiues, and attempted to deny the <hi>Popes</hi> ſecular iuriſdiction, when they proclaimed Fryer <hi>Paule</hi> of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Serui Theologo diſignato,</hi> and that by ſound of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet in S. <hi>Marks Piazzo?</hi> Haue I not heard my ſelfe the Women in the ſtrectes tell the Religious men and boyes of their <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> that they begged <hi>Eſcmofina per compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">To buy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> 
                     <hi>poma,</hi> and ſo denied them their accuſtomed releefe? Haue I not ſeene in ſome places of <hi>Italy,</hi> their Columns and Pillers of Stone paſted all ouer with inuectiues againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, and pardons to be bought out for ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as if our Sauiours wordes to the <hi>Iewes</hi> were now veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that if the people did not cry <hi>Hoſanna</hi> in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>es, the very ſtones would declare themſelues. From whence came the oppoſition of <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> againſt <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſecond, and the many diſcontents of the Nobilitie, the <hi>Popes</hi> chiefeſt <hi>Champions,</hi> againſt ſo dangerous a vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation? What ſay you to the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Mortmaine:</hi> the ſtopping of <hi>Peter</hi>-pence, and the interdicting of diuerſe <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ls,</hi> euen when <hi>England</hi> lay in the <hi>Cimerian</hi> mountaine of ſuperſtition, and was drowſie in the darkeſome caue of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>latry? Oh what a feare was the <hi>Pope</hi> in, when King <hi>Iohn</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21678:7"/> threatned the clergy, deſtroyed the order of <hi>Ciſteux,</hi> and baniſhed <hi>Stephen Langhton</hi> the kingdom. What thinke you of the bill put vp in Parliament the 11 of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. that if the king would take into his hands the lands diſordinately conſumed by the Clergy, not intermedling with tithes, or Biſhops liuings it would maintain 15. Earles, 1500. knights 6000. Eſquiers, 40. Almeſhouſes and bring 30000. pounds a yeere into the exchequer, ſo that you ſee by this, &amp; many more that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelues were not alwares pliant to the <hi>Popes</hi> beheſts, but broken out into diſordered raptures againſt the ambition, couetuouſnes, vſurpation, &amp; tyranny of <hi>Rome.</hi> And could all theſe things be done without the finger of God to point at <hi>Romes</hi> wickednes, or the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heauen, that <hi>Babilon</hi> muſt fall? anſwer a Gods name, you that muſt anſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe; and thus of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and effectuall contingents.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Probable Coniectures.</head>
                  <p>COncerning Probable coniectures, I raiſe them <note place="margin">Probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures.</note> from the deſcription of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in the word of God; and the comparing of the <hi>Popes</hi> doctrine, life, and actions to the ſame, as ſhall be made apparant in the next ſection, when I come to arraigne this deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Maieſty of God, the Prince of <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> the quietnes of mens conſciences, and the glorious progreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Iſaiah.</note> of the Goſpell. Doth not <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tell a ſtory of <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his fall, and Propheſieth of the deſtruction of <hi>Babilon,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iſaiah 46. Iſaiah 47.</note> and her <hi>Idols?</hi> whereby I make no doubt, but the abomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nations of <hi>Rome</hi> are perſonated, and all the wickednes of corrupt prelacy diſcouered: Nay? why ſhould I not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, what <hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Tirus,</hi> and compare, the <note place="margin">Ezech. 26.</note> wealth, pride, and preſumption of <hi>Rome</hi> to her ripening ſinnes, and at laſt rotten putrifaction: For wherein did euer any of the nations offend the moſt high God, but <hi>Popes</hi> haue exceeded, as by their owne authors is moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant: but if you come to <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie, hee will tell <note place="margin">Daniel 7. 8.</note>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21678:8"/> you of a litle horne amongſt the ten hornes; that had eies like a man, and a mouth ſpeaking great things; yea in the 11. <hi>verſe</hi> becauſe of the voice of the great wordes, which the horne ſpake, the beaſt was ſlaine, &amp; his body deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and giuen to the burning flame: but the puniſhment belongs to a more proper place. I now goe forward to the deſcription.</p>
                  <p>7. <hi>For the miniſtery of iniquity doth already worke, only hee</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Theſſal. 2. 7</note> 
                     <hi>which now with holdeth ſhall let, till hee be taken out of the way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. <hi>And then ſhall the wicked man be reuealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall aboliſh with the brightnes of his comming.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9. <hi>Euen him, whoſe comming is by working of Sathan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>10. <hi>And in all deceiueablenes of vnrighteouſnes amongſt them that periſh, becauſe they receiued not the loue of truth, that they might be ſaued.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11. <hi>And therefore God ſhall ſend them ſtrong illuſions, that they ſhall beleeue lies, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a litle before:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall ſit as God in the Temple of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And a little before:</p>
                  <p>He is called the <hi>man of ſinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in another place:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is the doctrine of Dinells forbidding meates, and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>mariages, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in another place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is named, the Whore of Babilon, the Cup of abomination,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc.</note> 
                     <hi>the beaſt with 7. heads and 10. hornes: Roma, ſepticollis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in many other places ſuch effectual deſcriptions, that I may well cry out, <hi>O God,</hi> What plainer words, what eaſier diſcouery, what would men deſire to know more concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the life of <hi>Rome,</hi> the doctrine of <hi>Rome,</hi> the impieties of <hi>Rome?</hi> Oh then anſwere a gods name, you that muſt anſwere before the iudgment throne of the Lambe, how comes this about, how could all theſe things be done without the finger of God to point at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21678:8"/> 
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> wickednes, or the reſolution of heauen, that <hi>Babilon</hi> muſt fall, and thus much of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> diſcouery: his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment followes with ſeuerall inditements.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Section 2.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Antichriſt Arraigned.</head>
                  <p>IN this ſecond ſection, or part of my diſcourſe; you ſhall haue the arraignment of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> vpon three ſeueral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditements. <note place="margin">The inditing of Popery.</note> The firſt for abſolutely contradicting the word of God, whereby he may truly be called the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi> 2. The ſecond for falſe doctrine, and foiſting in deuices of his owne, and trumperies of mens inuentions. 3. The third for abuſing the world with lying miracles, which the tempo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſers of this world, and lukewarme Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers doe mannerly call <hi>Piaefraudes,</hi> and orders of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="indictment">
                  <head>The firſt inditement againſt Antichriſt for contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting Gods Word.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the firſt. Though the <hi>author</hi> to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Contradicting the Scriptures. Heb. 6. 1.</note> aduiſe vs to goe more forward in our building of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> then laying a foundation of truth, yet he aſſureth vs, tht without a good foundation there is neither building, nor meanes to avoide diriſion: what ſhall wee ſay then to the deſpiſer of both, whoſe <note place="margin">Math. 7. 26.</note> impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty and preſumption haue not onely caſt corrupt handes on the ſacred word of truth, but inconſiderate Armes to tearein peeces the holy ſtructures, yea with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to pull the infants from the ſucking breſts of their ſweete mothers. To begin therefore with a ſtrong poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, <hi>Curſed</hi> be he, that doth either adde to my law, or <note place="margin">Deut. 12. 3. &amp; 4. 2. Ioſh. 1. 7. Prou. 30. 6. Reu. 11. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> dimiuiſh from ir, &amp;c. What helliſh furie durſt lay hold vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſecond <hi>Commandement,</hi> ſo that neither in their <hi>Ladies</hi> nor <hi>Ieſus Pſalter</hi> is it to be found. And come to the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21678:9"/> of their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God by pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitures, <note place="margin">Idolatry.</note> 
                     <hi>Images,</hi> &amp; pictures in priuat and publicke: in the Church and the ſtreetes: in the houſe in the cloſet: in the garments and <hi>Vtenſills:</hi> they are ſo farre from <hi>Apology</hi> diſtinction, or nicely, that the common people flie to their bookes ſhewing there is no mention of ſuch a prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, nor doe they any other, then the mother <hi>Church</hi> commandes. O vnheard-of madnes! O irreligious <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the firſt to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> the <hi>Originall</hi> hath it thus, <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>and bearing vp all things by his mightie word hath by himſelfe (or onely) Purged our ſinnes.</hi> Now behold what dares not <note place="margin">By himſelfe put out.</note> 
                     <hi>Sathan</hi> doe? deride God in the 2 of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> and tempt God in the 4. of <hi>Math.</hi> alleadging Scripture in both to ſerue his turne, yea drawing the bow home of ſacred truth to hit the marke of his aime, but what dares not the <hi>Pope</hi> doc? euen more then the diuell himſelfe; daſh away or quite extinguiſh ſuch places of Scripture, as may ſeeme to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his fictions, and lay his filthines to ouerture, and the hiſſing of the paſſengers. For in this text hee hath quite put out by himſelfe, and preſumed to put in merits, by-workes, both ſatisfactory and ſupererogatiue, trentalls, Maſſes, Dirges, and other trumperies full of Leprous ſteines and corruption, which I paſſe ouer becauſe they rather appertaine to the ſecond inditement.</p>
                  <p>In the 1 of <hi>Timothy</hi> 2. 5. The words are plaine, neither <note place="margin">1 Timoth. 2. 5. one Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</note> patible of other conſtruction, and I am ſure vnſufferable of contradiction. <hi>For there is one God, and one mediator betweene God and man, which is the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> But what dares not the <hi>Pope</hi> doe? quite reiect this, and with conceited ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy by way of compariſon argue thus; that as the necke is betweene the head, and the body, ſo the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> is betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> no graces or ſpirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences are granted from <hi>Christ,</hi> but they paſſe by the hands of his mothers interceſſion, and thus there is an <hi>Aue mary</hi> ſtill to obtaine preſent and future bleſſings: mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are done indeed in the <hi>Church,</hi> but by her meanes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21678:9"/> through <hi>Chriſts</hi> power, they haue afforded her attributes of redemption, ſauing, protection, defence, ruling, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding: for which purpoſe <hi>Leoes</hi> viſion is a fearefull and prodigious <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> wherein ſuch as aſcended the red ladder vnder <hi>Chriſt</hi> fell downe from diuers ſteppes but, ſuch as went vp the white ladder vnder the <hi>Virgin</hi> entred hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen without difficulty. If I ſhould proceede with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <note place="margin">Rom 8. 34. Heb. 7. 25. Math. 11. 28.</note> 34. <hi>Hebrewes 7. 25. Math.</hi> 11. 28. in which places <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our onely <hi>Mediator,</hi> and maketh interceſſion for vs, I muſt needes impute arrogancy, nay blaſphemy vnheard-of to the <hi>Papacy</hi> either to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er a <hi>Mediatrix,</hi> or pray to <hi>Saints</hi> for their aſſiſtance: but harken to more impietie; they haue deuiſed her to bee ſuch a boundles <hi>Ocean</hi> of goodnes, that ſhee many times entertaineth ſuch whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> refuſeth, yea they goe further in the glorifying of <hi>Saints,</hi> and crying to the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them. O vnlimitable audaciouſnes, and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous foppery! yet ſo manifeſt, and abſurdly entertained, that whole volumes are written in the defence, and as many about the diſcouery of the falſhood.</p>
                  <p>In the 5 of <hi>Iohn</hi> 39. It is plainely ſayd: <hi>Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 39. Reading the Scriptures. Act. 17. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>for in them you thinke to haue eternall life, and they are they, which teſtifie of me,</hi> whereupon it is recorded. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11. that the noble men of <hi>Theſſalonia,</hi> and <hi>Berea receiued the word with all readines, and ſearched the ſcriptures daily;</hi> to which purpoſe the holy Ghoſt yeeldeth a reaſon, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> 16. <hi>For the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration, and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to improue, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſnes.</hi> Now what Barbarous tyrany is this of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> worſe then Turkiſh crueltie, not onely to locke vp theſe pretious treaſures from the very eyes of ouer-looking, with a ſuppoſition of pollution by ignorance, but to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright the people with death, as by their bloody <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is apparant, if any daring hand, or hungry ſoule out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach at this heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> and looke with cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes toward mount Sion for their ſaluation: ſo that no lay man may preſume at all, nor others to read the word of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21678:10"/> God in the vulgar tongue.</p>
                  <p>In the 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14. the inhibition is not barely ſet <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. Againſt an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</note> downe for vſing an vnknowne language in the Church, or if you will in publike congregations, but illuſtrated with <hi>Similes,</hi> and excellent enforcements to diuert vs from ſuch abſurditie, and irregular abuſes in edifying. But alas how are our ſoules entangled, how is an inſupportable burthen of traditions thruſt vpon vs, how are we inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a tedious <hi>Catalogue</hi> of principles and Canons of the mother Church? And although the Apoſtles iuſtified the obeying of God before men, yet now. <hi>Non cuiuis licitum eſt dicere Papae, cur hoc faecis,</hi> Nay we muſt not aske a queſtion for conſcience ſake, nor ſay a prayer in our mother tongue for ſeare of <hi>Lutherano, diauoto, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico,</hi> and in the inquiſition to be clothed with the <hi>Sambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito,</hi> a puniſhment as vituperious as the carting of Bawdes in <hi>England.</hi> Nay if a modeſt ſinner ſhould but reueale thoſe diurnall liftings vp of the ſoule, which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> and other fathers call <hi>ciaculationes,</hi> and that to be done in their natiue ſpeech, it were ſufficient to bring them within the griping reaches of accuſation, and vnſatisfied ielouſie of alteration in religion, or repugnancy of the mother Church. O intollerable miſchiefe! and neuer heard of frency to runne away with ſuch madnes againſt God and his truth!</p>
                  <p>In the 20. of <hi>Mathew, ver.</hi> 20. the ſtorie of the mother <note place="margin">Math. 20. 20. Againſt ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ergy.</note> of <hi>Zebedcus</hi> children with that ſweete reprehenſion of ambitious tumors, is recorded at large. But how, not as barely exhortatory by way of defence of righteouſnes, humillitie, loue, patience, and other ſpirituall graces, but with forcible interdiction of, <hi>With you it ſhall not bee ſo:</hi> although the Lords of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> and other corrupt worldlings defiled with contaminating pride, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable affectings of authority, hunted after popular eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and eminency before others, yet would not Chriſt haue ſo much as elation of hart among his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, nor deſire of ſuperioritie ouer their brethren for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21678:10"/> any aſſumpted gift or grace whatſoeuer. Nay though it were true, that God had made their faith the rocke of foundation for his Church, and themſelues the Pillers and Lampes of his temple. But now behold the error of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the error ſaid I, the intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pride, and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> impietie, vſurpation, and inſatiable ſupremacy; hee muſt not onely exalt himſelfe aboue his brethren, and make that <hi>Conclauc</hi> of <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls</hi> an vndeniable Court of his greatnes and authoritie, but ſtand like a <hi>Coloſſus</hi> ouer the neckes of <hi>Princes,</hi> and as their own ſtories haue enlarged, preſumed to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the Crownes of <hi>Emperors</hi> with his feete; nay more then ſo? the <hi>Pope</hi> is carried on mens ſhoulders, and hath reached at heauen it ſelfe, and as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries report of <hi>Prometheus</hi> that ſtole <hi>Iupiters</hi> fiers, they haue with a <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride arrogated the name of God, and equalled their fictions and abſurd miracles with the beſt of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the mightieſt word of truth.</p>
                  <p>In the 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. 2. &amp;c. there are three fearefull attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes <note place="margin">1 Tim 4. 1. 2. Forbidding meates and marriages.</note> ſet downe, appropriate to ſuch as forbid marriages, and the eating of meat, which God hath ſanctified, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 1. <hi>Doctrine of Devills: 2. ſpeaking lyes through hypocriſie: 3. and haue their Conſcience burned with an hot iron;</hi> So that reaſonable ſoules are almoſt terrified with the Iudgement, and cannot thinke it poſſible to avoyde eternall flames, if they ſhould once attempt to croſſe the true meaning of the holy Ghoſt. Yet ſee, what man dare doe? the <hi>Pope</hi> hath inuented a law of <hi>Celebacy,</hi> a vow of chaſtitie, a deuiſe of ſequeſtration for <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and a manifeſt oppoſition to this veritie, denying marriage, which God honoured with his preſence, and branding it with the tearme of filthy pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and defiling copulation, nay, though that <hi>Chriſt</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed and named it honourable: Yet haue theſe Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries caſt a defiance in the face of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all what haue they done by way of conniuency, permitted Whoredome, and whereas they can ſay in ſome ſort; <hi>Si</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21678:11"/> 
                     <hi>non caſtè, tamen cautè,</hi> they haue publiſhed a greater audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in defending their contaminated hearts, and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate eyes. For they haue not ſpared to put to their hands and ſeales to the <hi>pattents</hi> of <hi>Abbots,</hi> and other religious perſons, wherein is this <hi>Proviſo: Licitum erit Domino no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro Abbatt ſemel in menſe habere mulierem ad purgandas renes.</hi> Nay, if I ſhould ſearch them further, I am affrayde of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended villany to march arme in arme with their adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and fornication: For by experience I alledge it, that in the Orchards of their Frieries and Nunneries, amongſt other exornations and furnitures of comelines, they haue whole trees of <hi>Sauine,</hi> and to what vſe that ſerues, <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Sauine.</note> and <hi>Mid-wiues</hi> know too well, and how it may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, an honeſt mother cannot relate without teares and wringing of handes.</p>
                  <p>As for meates they haue not onely limited vs in their vſe, but made a diſtinction of times, and ſet a ſeale vpon dayes, as if it were high treaſon to breake open the incloſures of ſuch inſtitutions, yea, an vnanſwerable offence to ſteppe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from their authoritie and limitation. Nay, though God ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> all that he made to be good, and bleſſed vs in the fruition of his bleſſings, though the Prophets haue curſed the obſeruers of dayes and times, new Moones, and feaſts: though <hi>Chriſt</hi> told his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that whatſoeuer went into the man did not defile him: though <hi>Peters viſion</hi> cleared that ſcruple of vncleaneneſſe in all meates, which God had ſanctified: yet is it a <hi>Pontificean</hi> verdict of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, to infringe the letter of their <hi>Lithurgie,</hi> and the people are made to beleeue, that the eating of white meats in Lent, will open the iawes of <hi>Hell</hi> ſo much the wider: O irrel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ious Religion, and <hi>Satanicall</hi> inuention!</p>
                  <p>In the twentith of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uiticus,</hi> God hedged in the <hi>Iewes,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Levit. 20. Marriage.</note> touching marriage, and enacted certaine precepts of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as binding voyces to all gouernments, kingdomes, and poſteritie: yet haue we not experience of the <hi>Popes</hi> repugnancie in this kinde? And that many vnlawfull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, as farre as <hi>Inceſt,</hi> haue beene borne withall, and had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21678:11"/> 
                     <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> benediction: yea, from their very Monaſteries, both Fryers and Nunnes haue beene taken out, to circle their heads with <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ronets,</hi> and fill their armes with bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowes, even contrary to their firſt footing in Religion, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mordiall contract with profeſſed holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>How plaine are thoſe words, 2. <hi>Theſ. 2. Matth. 24. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. 13. That that man of ſinne ſhould be reuealed, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is by the working of Sathan, with all power and ſignes, and lying wonders:</hi> Yet you ſee in deſpight of this, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion of the Predict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> dare be called <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-deus,</hi> as in the <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth. And <note place="margin">Miracles.</note> the Church of <hi>Italie</hi> produce ſo many Miracles, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of their owne Diuines haue made a ſtop in their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but I referre you to its proper place, that is, the third Inditement, which I frame in this accuſation; onely by the way conſider, how aduerſe this man is to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that dare iuſtifie himſelfe to be <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in this one poynt, as it were in deſpight of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>In the tenth of <hi>Iohn, Chriſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>My ſheepe heare my</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 10. Hearing the Word.</note> 
                     <hi>voyce:</hi> and in the twentie-one of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the 15. verſe. he bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Peter</hi> three times to feed his ſheepe, the reaſon is, becauſe it is apparant, that without Preaching neither can faith be obtained, nor God himſelfe ſo magnified, as he ought: but how poorely the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> diſtributes this gift, and in what broken Pipes the water runs from a ſparing Spring, I might ſay corrupted Fountaine, if not infectious ſtreame: let the impartiall Trauellers report, who haue viſited the Congregations on both ſides. For I dare be bold to ſay, that except ſome ſpeciall Citties, wherein Prieſts and Fryers diſcourſe of the Legend of Saints, magnifie the <hi>Popes</hi> ſupremacy, dilate of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urch, manifeſt the neceſſitie of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and pardons, and talke of Purgatory and Charitie to Monaſteries, the Countrey villages know not what a Sermon meaneth, onely M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe and Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tens, with ſome voraginous deliuery of wonders, and when they ieſture it in the beſt manner, not a place of Scripture alledged,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21678:12"/> nor a poynt of Diuinitie diſcuſſed, but ſome morall Precepts againſt notorious impreties, wherein yet the <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> and melancholly <hi>Stoickes</hi> went beyonde them.</p>
                  <p>In the 13. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the 35. verſe, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <note place="margin">Iohn 13. 35. Louing one another.</note> 
                     <hi>All men ſhall know, that you are my Diſciples, if you loue one another.</hi> But how well this Precept is obſerued amongſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> I appeale to themſelues, and their owne writings, what bitter inuectiues betweene <hi>Scotiſts</hi> and <hi>Thomiſtes?</hi> What fearefull raylings betweene <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Cardinals?</hi> What Calumniations betweene Fryers and Monkes? What deſperate quarrels betweene <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans?</hi> What ſcandalls betweene <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Seculars?</hi> before euer <hi>Watſons</hi> Booke of <hi>Quodlibets</hi> and <hi>Quidlibets</hi> excited laughter in ſome, deſpight in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>taſtings in all.</p>
                  <p>I could name patience and meekeneſſe as a marke of the Church of God, but to looke vpon the angry face of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the affrightings of Clergie <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> when their Religion is oppoſed, and fooleries derided, is more tyrannous, then the ten Perſecutions in the Primitiue Church; and the murthering the brethren in <hi>Turkey,</hi> is but a flea-biting to the burning and torturing of Martyres. In <hi>Portingall</hi> they brought one <hi>Gardner</hi> to death an Engliſhman, with ſuch vnheard-of crueltie, that the Clergie put a Deuills-coat vpon him, full of horrible ſhapes, gagd his mouth, hung him vp in chaynes, and made him liue in torments, when death tooke pittie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. How ridiculous was the burning of <hi>Paulus Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> and <hi>Bucers</hi> bones in the beginning of Queene <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> raigne, after three yeares bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all, and God knowes whether their bones or no. Such things are written of <hi>Bonners</hi> crueltie, beſides the Stories in the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents,</hi> that the inhumanitie exceedeth all the extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of Heatheniſh Tyrants. The other day when Fryer <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice</hi> could not bee caught in perſon, they burnt him in <hi>Rome</hi> by pourtraiture, and ſent twiſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21678:12"/> to murther him in priuate. Shall I name the miſchiefes againſt <hi>Queene Katherine Parre,</hi> in the latter end of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, by the workings of the Biſhops, eſpecially <hi>Gardiner?</hi> Shall I recite the murthers of the two Kinges of <hi>France,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and divers others, who ſeemed to oppoſe their diſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ered proceedings? It were a wonder to tell you, how Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all times, eſcaped their malice: but to end with the Powder plot, it muſt make an end of this Controuerſie, that the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is a meere Tyrant in earth, and the Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> moſt oppoſite to the Goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Humilitie,</hi> laſt of all is ſuch a marke of the true Church <note place="margin">Humilitie.</note> of God, that in diuers places, you haue the very garments of a <hi>Prophet</hi> named; <hi>Elias</hi> veſture; <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> nakedneſſe; <hi>Ieremies</hi> du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>geon; <hi>Amos</hi> frocke; <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſeameles coat; <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> Cammells hayre, and ſuch like. But the <hi>Pope</hi> muſt be a God on earth, and the <hi>Cardinalls</hi> take place of all <hi>Princes,</hi> that are not abſolute Monarkes. Their Caroſſes are ſo ſumptirous and ſtately, that they haue foure veluet chayres within, and ſixe ſtately Moiles without, and how they ride with publicke <hi>Curtezans</hi> to the Conclaue, is well knowne. <hi>Baptiſta Fulgoſus</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <note place="margin">Pride of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </note> that <hi>Peter Riarus,</hi> firſt a Fryer <hi>Minorite,</hi> afterward <hi>Cardinall</hi> to <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, had Gownes of cloth of Gold, Couerings and Tikes of Beds ſutable, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Furniture of the beſt Silke. There was a Feaſt made at Rome by a <hi>Cardinall</hi> to <hi>Elenor</hi> of <hi>Aragon,</hi> as ſhee went to marry <hi>Hercules de Eſt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> which laſted ſeauen houres, with all varietie of Muſicke, and delicate Acates, which had alſo playes and dances. Another <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> had a Concubine, called <hi>Tireſia,</hi> whoſe <hi>Chappinos</hi> were embroydred with Pearle and precious Stones, to an ineſtimable value. But what neede I goe ſo farre as <hi>Rome</hi> to inſtance this Inditement of oppoſing the Word of God againſt them, when I can name you ſuch Prelates in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21678:13"/> that for pride, and wealth exceed any Cardinalls of <hi>Rome,</hi> and liued, as if they would tell vs plainely, <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> was diſcouered, and there was neither heauen nor hell to bee thought vpon, but the preſent brauery of the world, and the magnificence of a Courtly and maieſticke life.</p>
                  <p>In the time of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> you had an <hi>Otho,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Baieux,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Kent.</hi> In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, you had a <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that affrighted the King with Excommunication. In the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, you had a Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> who gaue ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound for an Earledome. In the dayes of King <hi>Iohn, Stephen Langhton</hi> oppoſed the Maieſtie of <hi>England.</hi> In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> lent the King twentie thouſand pound. In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Cardinall Beuford</hi> was infamed for pride, and wealth. In the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, <hi>Woolſey</hi> writ, <hi>Ego &amp; rex meus,</hi> and ſo exceeded in magnificence and greatneſſe, that all Europe wondered at the proſperitie of our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and yet repined, that ſuch a <hi>Prince</hi> would endure the ambition and impietie of a Prelate. To conclude, Cardinall <hi>Poole</hi> was coſen to Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore endured for his magnificence and pompe: but yet all theſe belonged to the Church, and ſhould haue beene Preachers of the Word of God, but they proued Wolues in Sheepes clothing, and the humbled ſoule made this Vſe of their liues, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was diſcouered, and ſo beng the mayne Aduerſary, muſt needes oppoſe the Word of God, and doe contrary things to truth and Chriſtianitie. And thus much of his firſt Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="indictment">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21678:13"/>
                  <head>The ſecond Inditement of Antichrist for teaching <note place="margin">The ſecond inditement.</note> mens traditions, and foiſting into the doctrine of the Church, both Hereſies, errors, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities.</head>
                  <p>BEfore I goe any further, let mee anſwere certaine obiections, which I ſhould haue done in my former Inditement; namely what greater humillity can there bee, then for the <hi>Capuchines</hi> and Friers <hi>Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants</hi> to refuſe and deſpiſe the vanities of the world, and bee contented with pouertie, diſgrace, ſcornes, and neuer-heard of humiliation; inſomuch that <hi>Princes</hi> haue euen pricked their proud ſwelling hearts, and let out the corrupt blood, bringing them downe to proſtitution and contentment in Vnſauerie pouertie: as you ſaw, <hi>Duke Iogenx</hi> became father <hi>Angelo: Faelix</hi> of <hi>Sauoy</hi> thruſt himſelfe into a Monaſterie: <hi>Charles</hi> the fift forſooke the world, and left amongſt all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewells, as principall, his whippe of ſmall cordes, wherewith hee laſhed his ſides: and many other <hi>Princes</hi> finiſhed their dayes in Religious houſes. I anſwer with the <hi>Prophet,</hi> who required theſe things at your hands, and when it is the beſt humiliation it is contaminated and defiled with wrong circumſtances, and though it tend to the worſhipping of <hi>Angels,</hi> it is but diueliſh and <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. 23.</note> vnprofitable.</p>
                  <p>Againe, concerning outward garments, coules, weedes haire or hempen girdells, penance, whipping, faſting, <note place="margin">Kings.</note> and ſuch like tormenting the fleſh: is it any other, then the prieſts of <hi>Baall</hi> cutting and laſhing themſelues? then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dolatrous ſacrifices, wherein the Heathen practiſed the ſhedding of blood, and continued with Monſtrous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Diueliſh ſhapes to the people. <hi>Rent your</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioel.</note> 
                     <hi>hearts, and not your garments,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and when you faſt or mourne, hang not downe your heades like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21678:14"/> Bulruſſhes, or doe as <hi>Hipocrites</hi> doe, ſayth <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſt of all concerning good workes and releeuing the poore, which they tearme <hi>Charity;</hi> What profit can <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> ſuch things doe, where is preſumption of merit? what good can they procure, when they are full of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? why doe you plead for pouerty, when you grow ſo rich your ſelues, and fill your treaſuries with all manner of gifts from liuing and dying men? what talke you of religion? When you minde nothing but pollicies of State, and to trouble all <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> with deuiſes: as for the outward forme of good deedes I will bee bold to ſay wee haue had amongſt our ſelues more Colledges builded, Almes-houſes erected, Chappels edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Churches repaired, Poore relecued, Priſons viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Lands giuen to pious vſes, and that within theſe fiftie yeeres; then in two hundreth yeeres before, let them name what Countrie they pleaſe: and thus much for the Obiections, now to my purpoſe in hand.</p>
                  <p>To make you a Collection of all the deuiſes and tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> peries in Poperie, were to make a rope of ſand, and begin a worke which could haue no end: For this wodden wheele hath beene ſo often turned, that the Coggs are worne aſunder and either they muſt erect a new frame, or inuent a new ſuperſtition. For all the old is diſcouered, and in a Booke called the <hi>Bechine of the Romiſh Church,</hi> the face of reuelation, like your face in a glaſſe, will reflect vpon you. O that I neede bring you no further then that pulling hooke to ſhake the walls of Papiſtrie to rubbiſh, but becauſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie hath a paſſage of pleaſure among <hi>Noueliſts,</hi> I am contented to ſearch further, and thus expoſe vnto you, what I finde in other treaſuries.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond, in a certaine Sinod at <hi>Rome</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1059</label> that Chriſts body was preſent in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to bee handled with hand, and torne a peeces with teeth.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21678:14"/>
                  <p>In the Conuenticle of <hi>Florence</hi> the doctrine of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and the <hi>Popes</hi> ſupremacie was ratefied by the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1439</label> authoritie of that Sinode, and the doctrine of the ſeuen Sacraments propounded to the <hi>Arminians</hi> was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſo eſtabliſhed, that the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> agreed to the ſame, withall the other errors and ſuperſtitions of <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1564</label> 
                     <hi>Popery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, that the Apoſtles did firſt Preach the Goſpell and afterward deliuered the ſame in Scriptures, <note place="margin">Lib. 3. cap. 1.</note> that they might be a foundation and pillar of our faith; <note place="margin">Lib. 4. de. verb. cap. 4.</note> but <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſayth, they are neither neceſſary, nor ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent without traditions.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Scotiſts</hi> and moſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> maintaine, that the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary</hi> was neither conceiued in ſinne, nor euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any; and yet the Apoſtle ſayth, that by one man <note place="margin">Rom. 5. Galath. 3.</note> ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne went o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all, yea he ſheweth, that the Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne.</p>
                  <p>It is well knowne and publikely printed both in the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> doctrine of <hi>Collen,</hi> the workes of <hi>Thomas Aquinas, Bellarmine</hi> and others, that the Papiſts maintaine iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying by the Law, Merit by Workes, no neceſſity of confeſſion of faith, when yet the Scripture ſaith, Chriſt is made vnto vs iuſtice, wiſedome, Sanctification, and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.</note> Redemption, and that <hi>Abraham</hi> beleeuing, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him for righteouſnes, yea <hi>Iſaiah</hi> hath it thus <note place="margin">Iſayah 53.</note> in plaine tearmes, wee are healed by his ſtripes, the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in this manner. <hi>It is manifeſt, that no</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 3. Rom. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>man</hi> is iuſtified by the Law before God, and that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was not iuſtified by the workes of the Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nauarrus</hi> teacheth, that lay men may not diſpute of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ch. cap.</hi> 11. The Ch. <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a trinit.</hi>
                     </note> matters of faith vnder penaltie of the <hi>Popes</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and <hi>Linwood</hi> holdeth it ſufficient for lay men to beleeue the Articles of the Creed implicitely without publike confeſſion, or other <hi>Chriſtianlike</hi> yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a reaſon of their Saluation and good life.</p>
                  <p>Whereas our Sauiour ſaith <hi>Math. 11. My yoke is eaſie,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21678:15"/> 
                     <hi>and my burthen light. Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſets it downe thus, that the Precepts of the law, or the Goſpell, are more <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> greeuous and comberſome then the law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> and the cenſures of <hi>Collein</hi> with <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe ſay plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <note place="margin">2 queſt. 107.</note> that wee cannot bee ſaued, vnleſſe in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wee fulfill the Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> in his collection from the yeere 1256. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1256</label> aduertiſeth vs, that the Friers determining to ouerthrow the Goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> publiſhed another new one by the name of <hi>Euangelium aeternum,</hi> as if the word of God ſhould continue but for a time; to which they added cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fooleries out of the writings of <hi>Abbot Ioachim,</hi> and continued in ſuch blaſphemie, as if their deuiſes ſhould out-laſt the Goſpell of <hi>Saluation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Sentences determineth, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt might haue beene made man, <note place="margin">Lib. 3. diſt. 1.</note> and yet may, the maine Hereſie of the <hi>Patripaſſians;</hi> who held that the father ſuffered death for vs: and the ſcoolemen mainetaine, that the Sonne of God, might haue aſſumed the nature of a woman, which derogateth from the Miſterie of Chriſts incarnation. Beſides, they affirme, that Chriſt was neuer troubled in ſoule with any perturbation or affliction, contrary to the plaine <note place="margin">Iohn 12. Math. 26.</note> text of Scripture, <hi>Nam anima mea perturbata eſt,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, hee hath taken our will and our ſadnes vpon him.</p>
                  <p>The Maſter of the Sentences publiſheth, that all that <note place="margin">Lib. 4. diſtin. 1.</note> died vnder the Law, and not Circumciſed, were damned; and the Sinod of <hi>Trent</hi> pronounceth them <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> or accurſed, that ſay there are more or fewer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, then ſeuen, that is to ſay, 1. <hi>Baptiſme, 2. Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 3. the <hi>Euchariſt, 4. Penance, 5. Extream Vnction, 6. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and 7. Matrimony:</hi> and yet the miſterie of the great <note place="margin">Apoc 17.</note> Whore is called <hi>Sacramentum mulieris,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> neuer knew any more, then two, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> that is out of Chriſts ſides ſlowed water and blood, to which agrees <hi>Tertullian, Dioniſius, Are<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pagita, Chriſoſtom,</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21678:15"/> 
                     <hi>Cyrill, Gregory, Cyprian, Rabanus, Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>haſius:</hi> beſides, it is abſurde to thinke, that <hi>Marriage, Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſthood,</hi> and <hi>Penance</hi> were of one nature vnder the Law, and another vnder the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nauarrus</hi> in his <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes <note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Sacr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 14.</note> of the Sacraments, maintaine, that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new Law both containe grace and conferre grace, <hi>Ex opere operato,</hi> which alſo may appeare by the Canons of the ſeauenth <hi>Seſſion</hi> of <hi>Trent.</hi> But Lord, what abſurdities muſt now follow? Firſt, to attribute as much to Matrimony, Confirmation, and extreame <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> as to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Lordes Supper.</hi> Secondly, What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie is this for <hi>Prieſtes</hi> to forſweare marriage, ſeeing it containeth grace, and worketh it. Thirdly, If grace be nothing elſe but Charitie, or a habit not diſtinct from it, how may Charitie be contayned in Oyle, or the rites of Matrimony, or externall ſignes. Fourthly, Who can ſhew, or dare maintaine, that ſuch as receiue their Popiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, orders, extreame <hi>Vnction,</hi> or are married, are more iuſt, then they were before. Fiftly, Laſt of all God hath promiſed to worke by his Sacraments, but wee doe not reade, that euer he promiſed Iuſtification, or grace to married folke, or to ſuch as are greaſed by extreame <hi>Vnction,</hi> or to any ſuch, who with <hi>Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmine</hi> and <hi>Caniſius</hi> ſay, that Sacraments are onely externall ſignes, whereby it muſt needes follow, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> body and blood in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> are no Sacrament, becauſe they appeare not to the eyes nor are apprehended by other ſences.</p>
                  <p>By the effects of holy water ſprinkling, and waſhing, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> hope to be clenſed from ſinnes, but the <hi>Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robaptiſts</hi> among the <hi>Iewes</hi> were therefore reputed <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> affirmeth; and the <hi>Prophets</hi> tell vs, that neither <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mus,</hi> nor thouſands of riuers of Oyle, neither riuers, nor the whole Ocean can purge or purifie vs from our tranſgreſſions.</p>
                  <p>In thoſe dayes, the <hi>Doſitheans</hi> were reputed <hi>Heretiques,</hi> for affectation of Virginitie, and puniſhing their bodies.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21678:16"/> yet now the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are tranſported with another Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, yea, many others. For the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23. for denying the immortalitie of the ſoule; yet ſuch is the corruption of nature, and impietie of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Popes,</hi> Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean <hi>Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. <hi>Clement</hi> the 7. and diuers other <hi>Popes</hi> borrowed this Hereſie from the <hi>Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> or rather <hi>Epicurean Philoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>phers,</hi> and blaſphemed God in their repugnancy: yea that beaſtly opinion of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaites</hi> concerning the eating of the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> really, was maintained by Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> in a certaine Chapter beginning; <hi>Ego Berergarius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was deteſted by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> money to buy the graces of the <hi>Spirit:</hi> What ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Mart of Maſſes, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tſaile of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, chaffring for Benefices, and ſelling all things for money, more execrably, then euer <hi>Iudas</hi> did <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As for that ſmall account, or ſlighting the ſinne of vſing common Women, hearken I pray you, what is recorded of Saint <hi>Auſten; Docebat deteſtandam turpitudinem indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renter vtendi faminis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you reade Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, you ſhall finde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Heretickes</hi> condemned for doing thoſe thinges, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">Heretickes.</note> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe now tranſgreſſe, and inueigh againſt true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> for reputing their Doctrine loathſome. The <hi>Baſileans</hi> by <hi>Irenaus</hi> were eſteemed <hi>Heretickes</hi> for <hi>Images,</hi> Enchantments, and diuers ſuperſtiticus exorcizations. <hi>Carpocrates,</hi> and <hi>Marcellina</hi> one of his followers, adored the Images of <hi>Ieſu, Paul, Homer,</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras:</hi> and who doth not know, what eſtimation <hi>George</hi> the Dragon-kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Saint <hi>Katherine,</hi> aed <hi>Papia</hi> haue in <hi>Europe?</hi> And the <hi>Marcoſians</hi> were condemned for Baptizing in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Language, and annointing with <hi>Chriſme,</hi> &amp;c. Witneſſe all this, and much more <hi>Ireneus</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Meſſalians</hi> were condemned for vſing much bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and multiplicitie of prayers: What thinke you then of the <hi>Papiſts Roſary,</hi> and certaine numbers of <hi>Creedes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21678:16"/> and <hi>Pater-noſters.</hi> The <hi>Angelikes</hi> and <hi>Caians</hi> inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Angels, which Hereſie proceeded from <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and is diſallowed of by <hi>Epiphanius, Tertullian, Auſtin,</hi> and others, and yet the <hi>Papiſts</hi> haue ſtill a Maſſe in the honour of <hi>Angels.</hi> The <hi>Seuerians</hi> are traduced for forging of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> and one <hi>Philumena</hi> accuſed for drawing a loaſe of bread out of a narrow mouthed glaſſe, but what is this to the Papiſts <hi>Legend?</hi> And how can <hi>Bellarmine</hi> make mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles <note place="margin">Auſtin. c. 24. Haereſ.</note> a marke of the Church, or other <hi>Ieſuites</hi> maintaine the notorious abſurdities of <hi>Popery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if it be thus, that theſe things are prooued againſt them, that infinite thouſandes of errours, like ſo many <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts</hi> in a filthy ſtanding lake, increaſe to an vnſufferable fulſomneſſe in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that diuers reformed places haue yet cleanſed themſelues from their pollution, and that the true ſeruants of God doe daily riſe, like the childe <hi>Daniel,</hi> to examine the hypocriſie and vnſauoury luſt of the Iudges. O let no i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dicious men for any worldly reſpect whatſoeuer, come ſo neere the Chariot wheeles of this <hi>Strumpet,</hi> as to be daſht with the filth and durt, which it caſteth vp: let the true ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of God come out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell.</hi> For queſtionles it will fall, and then whoſoeuer ſhall preſume of her ſtrength, glory, and mightineſſe, will bee preſſed, and ouer-whelmed with her rubbiſh, if they tarry within: let all regenerate ſoules come to the pure ſtreame of the Scriptures to drinke the waters of life, and not ſeeke the pudled filth and noyſome lake of mens deuiſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, which muſt needes either choake with the mudde of ſuperſtition, or poyſon with the venome and mixture of vnequall impoſitions. As for pollicie, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, making leagues, ciuill honeſtie, and ſuch like for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearances, with ſo great an aduerſary to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Why ſhould not the <hi>Iewes</hi> vſe the language of <hi>Canaan?</hi> Why did <hi>Ioſuah</hi> tell the people, he and his houſe would ſerue God? Why did <hi>Iob</hi> cry out, though thou kill me, I will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee? Why did <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Micha</hi> proue <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> to foure hundred falſe <hi>Prophets?</hi> Why did <hi>Amos</hi> oppoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21678:17"/> 
                     <hi>Amaſiah?</hi> Why did all the <hi>Prophets</hi> ſtand in the gappe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corruption of time, and the mayne currant of the world? Why did <hi>Chriſt</hi> weepe for the hardneſſe of mens hearts, and call the <hi>Prieſtes, Phariſes, Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Lawyers, hypocrites?</hi> Why did <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſe, that after the way they called Hereſie, he ſerued the God of his fathers? Anſwere a Gods name, you that muſt anſwere before the iudgement throne of the Lambe: How comes this about, if the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe at laſt be deſtroyed, after the man of ſinne is conſumed with the breath of Gods noſtrills? But we will yet goe forward. For there are more muſtred Armies readie to march vpon them, and come to the charge, to their vtter ouer-throw and execution.</p>
                  <p>Shall I now name certaine blaſphemies, and nefarious actions committed by the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues, and borne withall, or publiſhed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> by which you may ſee, how this Inditement is vnanſwerable, and there muſt needes follow a Iudgement of condemnation after the Arraignement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beno</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> recites a ſtory, that <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted <note place="margin">Fearefull acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Popes.</hi>
                     </note> with his God in the Hoſt, or the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could receiue no anſwe of it againſt the <hi>Emperor,</hi> he threw the Sacrament into the fire: and <hi>Pius</hi> the fift, caſt an <hi>Agnus De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> into <hi>Tyber,</hi> and burnt another, as <hi>Hierome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tena</hi> affirmes. <hi>Clement</hi> the 6. would haue men pray and cry to the <hi>Pope, Lord</hi> open thy treaſure the fountaine of liuing <note place="margin">Ch: Vnigenit. ext.</note> water. <hi>Horatius Turſellinus</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Peter Adobran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dini</hi> ſayth, that God made the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> as much as could be the companion of his <hi>Mateſtie,</hi> And <hi>Bernardine</hi> with <hi>Bonauenture,</hi> giue her power ouer her ſonne, <hi>Iure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                     </note> In the Roman breu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary, ſhee is called <hi>Dulcis amica Dei:</hi> and in the <hi>Miſſall</hi> of <hi>Sarum,</hi> the Sauiour of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alloweth a ſaying of the Fryers to the Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe, thou haſt redeemed vs, thou haſt reconciled vs to the Father.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Saracens</hi> honor the bookes of the Olde <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21678:17"/> Teſtament, but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> prophane the Scriptures. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> call it, a killing letter. <hi>Stapleton</hi> endeuors to proue, that all Hereſies proceed from the <hi>Scriptures. Kelliſon</hi> ſayth, that the Deuill doth wappe himſelfe from toppe to toe in Scriptures. <hi>Turrian</hi> writing againſt <hi>Sadeel,</hi> calleth the Scriptures <hi>Delphicum gladium,</hi> an Inſtrument to all purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> accuſeth them as imperfect and inſufficient. <hi>Piggius</hi> and <hi>Eckius</hi> miſ-termeth them a dead Letter. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Poole,</hi> an Incky Goſpell. <hi>Montanus,</hi> a noſe of Waxe. and many others, a Ship mans-hoſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Steuchus</hi> in his Treatiſe for the defence of <hi>Conſtantines</hi> donation, calleth the <hi>Pope</hi> a <hi>God;</hi> and the Abbot <hi>Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Blaſphemies.</note> expreſly ſayth, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> haue but one Conſiſtory. <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, vpon Eaſter day fought with the <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Rauenna. Gregory</hi> the 7. muſtred his Armie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. on good Fryday, and thought to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Emperour</hi> in Saint <hi>Maries</hi> Church, by throwing a ſtone vpon him from a vault. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. euen at the eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacrament, endeuoured to kill <hi>Laurence</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Volater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>de medices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Although <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. called the Goſpell a Fable, and the wicked and monſtrous liues of the <hi>Popes</hi> were euer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered: yet did the people fall downe like beaſtes before them, worſhipping them as God: and <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, <note place="margin">Lib. 2.</note> how the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> of <hi>Sicily</hi> cryed thus to the <hi>Pope;</hi> Thou that takeſt away the ſinnes of the world haue mercie vpon vs. To which purpoſe, <hi>Simon Begnius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druſa,</hi> calleth <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. his Sauiour; and <hi>Stapleton</hi> writing to <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. tearmeth him <hi>Supremum numen in terris,</hi> and theſe attributes follow; The vicar of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the <hi>Church,</hi> the head, the ſpouſe, the foundation of the <hi>Church:</hi> yea <hi>Thomas Waldenſes</hi> flattereth <hi>Martin</hi> the 5. with <hi>Salua nos Domine, perimus;</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> in the conuenticle of <hi>Trent,</hi> calleth the <hi>Pope</hi> the light which came into the world.</p>
                  <p>But now if you would demand the reaſon of all theſe blaſphemies, and filthy wickednes, it is apparant by a <hi>ſimile</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21678:18"/> of bitter ſtreames from ſower ſprings: theſe things were <note place="margin">Authors. <hi>Beno. Platina. Nauclecus. Theoderick.</hi>
                     </note> deuiſed and maintained by ſuch men, as were branded in their liues for notorious and infamous liuers. <hi>Benet</hi> the 9. and <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the 2. gaue themſelues to the Deuill. Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie two Popes practiſed Magicke. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth was condemned for a <hi>Negromantick</hi> at a Councell: and the Councell of <hi>Piſe</hi> accuſed <hi>Gregory</hi> the 12. and <hi>Benet</hi> the 13. for wicked liuers. <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. was an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that is, beleeued there was no God. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> was conuinced for making queſtion of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. and <hi>Clement</hi> the 7. were alſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Atheiſts: Paul</hi> the 3. conſulted with the Deuill, and <hi>Iulius</hi> the 3. ſayd, he would eat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>diſpetto di Dio:</hi> yea <hi>Boc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cace</hi> in his ſecond <hi>Nouell,</hi> bringeth in a <hi>Iew</hi> wondring how the Cittie of <hi>Rome</hi> ws kept from ſincking to <hi>Hell,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſinnes and abominations both of the <hi>Popes,</hi> the gouernment, and the people.</p>
                  <p>Here might properly be brought in certaine proofes and enlargements: 1. That <hi>Popery</hi> is a ſinke of Heatheniſh <hi>Idolatry:</hi> 2. That their religion neuer came from true <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> 3. That it was neuer taught by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles:</hi> 4. That it was not knowne to auncient profeſſed <hi>Emperours,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Kinges:</hi> 5. That the auncient <hi>Brittaines</hi> were not conuerted to the now Popiſh religion. 6. That Popiſh religion is falſely called <hi>Catholicke:</hi> 7. That there were neuer ſuch doctrine, and principles in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Church: 8. That it is repugnant to auncient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels: 9. That it is contrary to the Fathers of the Church: 10. That it was neuer teſtified by the blood of Chriſtian Martyres, &amp;c. But it would proue too great a mountaine of amaſement, and be extended to a greater volume, then I propoſe, therefore I referre you to ſuch ſufficient authors as are euery where extant, for the good of all <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Maſſe by their owne confeſſion was framed at ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall <note place="margin">Popery a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane deuiſe.</note> times, and by diuers authors. For how euer the law of God was giuen at an inſtant, and the Goſpell of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> with the doctrine of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> compriſed in one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21678:18"/> volume, called the <hi>Teſtament,</hi> yet hath this ſabricke of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery beene many hundred yeares a framing, and the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls come into millions of handes, that had not time to this houre to diſpatch the building, and couer the ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Thus <hi>Walafridus, Platina, Nauclerus,</hi> and others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: that <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> made the <hi>introit, Iudica me Deus: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> added the confeſſion: <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Antiphona</hi> and <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie eleeſon: Teleſphorus, gloria in excelſis:</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius</hi> certaine clauſes of the Oriſons: <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> deuiſed the office on <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day: but who contriued the Maſſes for <hi>S. Francis, S. Dominicke,</hi> and other late Saints, the Papiſts themſelues cannot tell. The <hi>Pſalter</hi> of our <hi>Lady</hi> was inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Bonauenture.</hi> You ſee the Prieſts offer Chriſt for the ſinnes of the quicke and dead, for ſicke horſes, and piggs, &amp;c. I hope you all thinke this a deuiſe of man, and in no Scripture at all. Oh <hi>Ieſus,</hi> didſt thou ſpit, and ſalt, or light Candles in Baptiſme? Didſt thou vſe any mimicke geſtures when thou inſtitutedſt the Sacrament of thy Supper? Is it not a ſtrange deuiſe, that no Prieſt may ſay Maſſe without water and fire? The worſhip of the Sacrament and the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie thereof in a Pixe was inuented by <hi>Honorius.</hi> What thinke you of <hi>Canonicall</hi> houres, and the reliques of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, who deuiſed them I pray you? All their Letanies and Prayers to Saints and Angells, yea, peraduenture to ſuch as are gone to the Deuill, as the Heathen canonized ſuch for Gods, as were lecherous and inceſtuous perſons, were framed by ſundry Popes and Fryers. The Popes tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple crowne, kneeling to the Croſſe, and a thouſand of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trumper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, were the excrements of hot braines, and men, who knew no better, or at leaſt would not, then to increaſe their honor, and ambition, and wealth. The feaſt of <hi>Iubile</hi> was ordained by <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. <hi>Corpus Chriſts</hi> by <hi>Clement</hi> the 5. Of our <hi>Ladies</hi> conception by <hi>Sixtus quartus,</hi> of her aſſumption by another; and all the reſt of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and ſuperſtitious rites by one wicked Pope or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſt or other. For becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd, the reſt I will ſet in order when I come, theſe men haue aſſumed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21678:19"/> a power to deuiſe vnheard-of impieties, and yet as Phyſicians guild their bitter pills with ſome flouriſhing golden vertue; they ſtoppe all mens mouthes with order, and ordinances of the <hi>Church:</hi> but the Saints of God can tell them, that <hi>Ieroboams</hi> calues were erected by order. For the Text ſaith, the King called a councell: and the Statutes of <hi>Omri,</hi> with all the abominations of the Prieſtes, and Kinges of <hi>Iſraell</hi> were confirmed, and maintained by order; therefore order diſordred may turne to confuſion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. And ſo I proceede.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> of <hi>Luzenburg</hi> ſheweth, how the Doctors of <note place="margin">Popiſh deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes agree with Heatheniſh cuſtomes.</note> 
                     <hi>Collen</hi> auerred, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was the forerunner of Chriſt <hi>in naturalibus,</hi> as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt in diuinis,</hi> and that they would proue the diſtinction of the three perſons in Trinitie by <hi>Philoſophy. Gratian</hi> talking of diuers orders, and degrees in <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cretis diſt. 21.</note> the <hi>Roman Hierarchy,</hi> confeſſeth, that this difference was deduced from the <hi>Gentiles: Gregory</hi> the 1. writing to <hi>Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> permitted the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to build boothes in the day of the dedication of their Churches, and to kill Oxen for the <note place="margin">Beda lib 1. cap. 30.</note> prayſe of God; and was not this the cuſtome of the <hi>Pagans</hi> ſeruing Idols. <hi>Boniface</hi> the 4. conſecrated the Church called <hi>Pantheon</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> where <hi>Cibele</hi> and all the Heathen gods were adored, to our <hi>Lady</hi> and all Saints, as if he would ſhew, that the worſhip of Saints muſt ſucceed in the place of Idols, and Heathen gods. Who knowes not, that the Prieſtes of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did ſhaue their heades and beards, the Prieſtes of <hi>Baal</hi> launce themſelues, the Prieſts of <hi>Cibele</hi> whippe themſelues, and the Prieſts of <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> made the King beleeue, the Idoll did eat vp his prouiſion? and who ſees not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtifie the imitation, and yet as the Lapwig runneth away with the ſhell on her head, they carry it with zeale, deuotion, and auſteritie of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. <hi>Bellarmine, Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and others, proue the Popiſh <hi>Monarchy</hi> by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> gouernment: the ſeauen Sacraments by Philoſophicall arguments, and that one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may be in many places at once by <hi>ſophiſticate</hi> principles. Is not the worſhip of Saints and Images a meere tricke of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21678:19"/> the Gentiles, and are not all the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſes of adoration ſprung from helliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dolatrie? The temple of <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Rhemus</hi> is now the Church of Saint <hi>Coſmas</hi> and <hi>Damianus,</hi> the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Faunus</hi> is conuerted into the Church of S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> The temple of <hi>Iuno Cupra</hi> into the Chappel of our <hi>Lady</hi> of <hi>Loretto,</hi> where the altar ſtood dedicated to <hi>Apollo,</hi> is now one erected to Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; the Image of Braſſe of <hi>Iupiter</hi> is now Saint <hi>Peters,</hi> as their antiquaries iuſtifie. There was one ſupreme God among the Gentiles, and many inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors vnder him, ſo the <hi>Papiſts</hi> acknowledge one God in tearmes, but haue an hundred inferiors for euery action and diſeaſe: the burning of incenſe commeth from the Gentiles, and they aſſite <hi>Virgils</hi> teſtimony with other prets, the waſhing of hands, their skippings and turnings, their ſacrifices with fire and water, their tunickes, <hi>Albes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pompous ceremonies, their Purgatory and beliefe of good and bad <hi>Genius,</hi> their worſhip, of trees, ſtones, and fountaines with infinite other abſurdities &amp; abominations, are all the deuiſes of Gentils, and cuſtomes of <hi>Pagans:</hi> which if it be ſo, Anſwere a Gods name, you that muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe, how comes this about; if the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe at laſt be deſtroyed, after <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and the man of ſinne conſumed with the breath of Gods noſtrills?</p>
                  <p>I muſt beginne with a ſmile. For you cannot chooſe, <note place="margin">Popery kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> but laugh when you heare of the Colliers faith to beleeue, as the Church beleeues, though it was not knowne, what that beliefe was, the obſcuring of the Scriptures, the inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of their reading, their praying in an vnknowne tongue, their not ſuffering men to diſpute, their preaching of ſtories and tales without one word of edifing, their ſuppreſſing of religious bookes, and infinit other palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enormities, what are they any other, but inſtrumentes of <hi>Sathan</hi> to keepe vs in ſecuritie, or <hi>Synens</hi> hands to rocke the Cradle of our frailtie, till wee fall a ſleepe yea ſnort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the <hi>Cimerian</hi> caue of darkenes, ignorance, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21678:20"/> ſuperſtition. Oh harken for Gods ſake what Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers write of ignorance, dulnes, and ſtupidity in ſpirituall affaires. <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro lib. 1. de haereſi.</hi> ſayth that diuers <hi>Popes</hi> were vtterly vnlearned. <hi>Lazier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Author <hi>Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </note> ſpeaking of <hi>Gregory.</hi> 6. reciteth, that he cauſed another to be conſecrated with him for ſaying Maſſe, becauſe hee himſelfe ſcarce knew a letter, but this matters not, for <hi>Ielium</hi> approues, that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot be depoſed for want of learning. <hi>Pope Zachary</hi> condemned <hi>Virgilius</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Germany</hi> as an heretike for ſaying, there were <hi>Antipodes. Paul</hi> the ſecond was ſo vnlearned, that he determined them to bee Heretikes, that named the word <hi>Academy. Iohn Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham</hi> in the <hi>Prouinciall</hi> conſtitution ſuppoſeth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cient for Prieſts either by themſelues or ſubſtitutes, once a yeere, to tractate, or at the moſt euery quarter, of the ten Commandements, of the law, the twelue Articles, the two commandements of the Goſpell, the ſeuen workes of mercy, the ſeuen deadly ſins, the ſeuen vertues, and the ſeuen ſacraments without curioſitie, or putting it home to edifying &amp; vſes of the conſcience. <hi>Durandus</hi> teacheth, that the two points of a Biſhops Miter ſignifies the old and new Teſtament, but <hi>Lewis marcilius</hi> an <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Frier ſaid that the ſtropps of the Miter, which the Biſhop hangs at his backe did foreſhew, that they neither vnderſtood old nor new Teſtament. <hi>Aluarus Pelagius</hi> complaines, that the Biſhops of <hi>Spaine</hi> committed thouſands of ſoules to yong nouices, that were fitter to play with Apples and Peares; ſhall I name the Sermons of the Frier <hi>Menot, Maillard, Bromyard,</hi> and their fellowes, they were ſo full of ridiculous fables that the people went to Church to ſport themſelues in the hearing. The <hi>Germans</hi> of late complained to <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. that Biſhops aduanced vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ideots, vnfit, vilde, and ridiculous. It is well known, that many Prieſts and Friers could not ſay Maſſe, nor diſtinguiſh of dayes, but by the great letters; and all your Schoolemen and Inquiſitors generally fill their ſtudies with bookes of <hi>Rhetorike,</hi> ſtories, legends <hi>Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21678:20"/> Canons, Ciuell law</hi> and ſuch traſh. For is not ſtubble traſh compared to the come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but neither Bible nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors of Scriptures, ſcarce a father or diuine author ſhall bee found amongſt them, for in truth how euer now a daies they ſwell with the tumor and accent of great Schollerſhip and learning, they are ſtill for the moſt part illiterate, and ignorant, and that reputation they haue, proceedeth either from their auditors and diſciples want of knowledge, or their Gloſſes, and tedious <hi>Cataloging</hi> of vncertaine authors, who handle curious queſtions, and at the beſt ſchool-diuinitie.</p>
                  <p>Nouation cannot ſtand without Chriſtian pollicie, nor <note place="margin">Popery repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the lawes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> pollicie bee maintained without obſeruation and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of othes, promiſes, compacts, leagues and treaties of trade and commerce: yet you ſhall ſee, what either the ſcorne of <hi>Papiſt,</hi> negligence, preſumption, equinocation, or one tricke or other hath done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Formoſus</hi> being depoſed for-ſwore his Biſhopricke, yet regarded not his oath, but reſumed the ſame. In the life of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperour, <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. was inueſted <hi>Pope</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his oath. <hi>Paſchall</hi> the ſecond, ſolemnly ſwore to the Emperour being his priſoner, but at leaſt ſubiect to his danger, that hee would keepe and religiouſly obſerue the Articles ſet downe betweene them, bur hee proued ſo falſe &amp; repugnant that after he had eſcaped, he rebelled and excommunicated the Emperour. <hi>Charles</hi> the French <note place="margin">Theodori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k:</note> King cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>geth <hi>Gregory</hi> 12. and <hi>Benedicke</hi> 13. of violation of their faith, and <hi>Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>phrius</hi> alleadgeth againſt <hi>Alexander</hi> 6. that hee was a delinquent in more then <hi>punicke</hi> perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Guicciardine</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Climent</hi> 7. ſayth plainely <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra di poca ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de, Iulius, 2. Leo</hi> 10. and diuers others endeuored to proue, that the <hi>Pope</hi> was not bound by any oath, but he might both infring the ſame and incite others to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable practiſes. <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. as <hi>Helmoldus</hi> complaines ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the <hi>Pope</hi> for the rebellion of his ſubiects, and this by his inſtigation the tumults of <hi>Germany</hi> were raiſed, and the people ſet all in combuſtion vpon the <hi>Popes</hi> warrant
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21678:21"/> and pardon, In the Counſell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and his complices perſwaded the Emperour to violate the ſafe conduct of <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> whereupon that damnable poſition of <hi>fides non eſt conſernanda cum hereticis,</hi> was ratified, and concluded; which if it bee ſo, what truſt can bee ſecured of any contract or treatie, but ſtill vpon aduantage the aduerſary will breake out, and imitate the <hi>Panther</hi> who ſheweth not her tallents, till the beaſts be within her reach? Did they not of late dayes perſwade the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> 5. to breake with <hi>Luther<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Paul</hi> the 3. in a Bull againſt <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 8. denounced them accurſed, that would not infringe all oathes and alleageance either couenanted with the King, or his ſubiects. <hi>Eugen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us</hi> 4. was the cauſe or motiue that <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> infringed his oth with the <hi>Turke. Innocentius</hi> the 3. blew vp that winde of rebellion againſt King <hi>Iohn.</hi> And <hi>Pius</hi> the firſt curſed heauen and earth, that he could thriue no better againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregoey</hi> 7. contrary to all the lawes of honor and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons impriſoned the Emperors Embaſſadors, and another killed the Emperor <hi>Fredericks</hi> Embaſſadors, who brought good newes of the ſucceſſe in <hi>Paleſtina.</hi> I will not name the Marquis of <hi>Montigni</hi> and Earle of <hi>Bergnes</hi> ſent into <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heſmoldus</hi> author.</note> 
                     <hi>Spaine,</hi> who were put to death by the Inquiſitors. <hi>Paſchall</hi> 2. and his adherents armed the ſonne againſt the father. <hi>Gregory</hi> 9. performed the like by <hi>Henry</hi> the ſonne againſt <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. witnes <hi>Auentinus. Innocentius</hi> 3. confounded whole kinreds with inteſtine warre. <hi>Marius Belga</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that <hi>Gregory</hi> 4. was the radical cauſe of <hi>Ludouicus Pius</hi> warres, when his children rebelled. But what ſay you to <hi>Alphouſus Dias,</hi> that came poſt from <hi>Rome</hi> to haue his owne brother murthered for embracing the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>If I ſhould goe forward in the diſcouery of all the errors, Hereſies, and abſurdities in <hi>Popiſh</hi> religion, I ſhould looſe my ſelfe in a labyrinth, wander in a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and though I were a good ſwimmer, yet proue like a man entangled in weedes ready to ſincke without ſome
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21678:21"/> charitable ſupportation: therefore I will caſt vp no more earth vpon this banke, but referre you to other mens groundes, where you ſhall haue minds of all manner of mettalls, and ſo you may repaire to thoſe furnaces, that trie gold from droſſe, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew you the puritie of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the durt and filth of Poperie; onely one word concerning the authoritie and pretogatiue of Kings which the <hi>Popes</hi> haue endeuored to impaire and by all meanes to diſanull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 3. compareth the Pope to the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <note place="margin">Popery prei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ceth the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Princes.</note> the Emperour to the <hi>Moone, Cap. de maior, &amp; obed: Clement</hi> the 5. in the <hi>Chap. Romani princip.</hi> auou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heth, that the Emperours haue ſubmitted their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eades to the Biſhop, and how they ought to take an oath of fealtie and obedience to the Pope. In the <hi>Chap. Paſtoralis,</hi> the Pope determineth that by right of the papacy hee hath ſuperioritie ouer the <hi>Empire,</hi> and that in the <hi>Vacancy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> hee himſelfe is Emperour. <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. writing to the French King gaue him to vnderſtand, that hee was the Popes ſubiect, <hi>Scire &amp; Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp;c.</hi> and therefore hee had two ſwordes to inueſt and depoſe Kings, as well as the Keies to open and locke the dores of heauen. <hi>Ioſephus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſtanus, lib. de oſculat. pedum</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 5. cap 6. de pontif Rom.</note> 
                     <hi>Pontif.</hi> inferreth, that the Pope may depoſe the Emperour. In the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> the 5. againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Pope dares preſumptuouſly affirme, that hee is made a Prince and ſet ouer all nations and kingdomes to diſſipate and ſpoile, to plant and to build &amp;c. yea in the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> new <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1594</label> doctrine <hi>Bella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mine</hi> ſaith, that the Pope hath power to change kingdomes, and to take from one to retribute to another. <hi>Chincard</hi> a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> was hangd in <hi>Paris</hi> for writing diuers ſeditious poſitions concerning the Popes authority in diſpoſing of the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> and tranſplanting it from the family of <hi>Burbon. William Rainold</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man vnder the name of <hi>Roſſe</hi> doth in expreſſe tearmes defend the league againſt the <hi>French</hi> King: and affirmeth, that the right of all kingdomes is layed vpon the Popes foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherevpon as in ſome ſort you haue heard before, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21678:22"/> the 7. raiſed the wars of <hi>Germanie</hi> againſt <hi>Henry</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Paſchall</hi> 2. raiſed the ſon to rebell againſt the father, whereby hee was taken priſoner and ſo reſigned, but yet the Pope proſecuted the ſonne with as great hatred, as the father. <hi>Innocentius</hi> 2. went by force of armes to conquer <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and had ſurely done it, if the ſonne had not ſuccored and aſſiſted his father. <hi>Adrian</hi> 4. and <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. did ſo preuade againſt <hi>Frederick</hi> 1. that hee held the ſtirrop to the one, &amp; was trod vpon by the other. <hi>Celeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in</hi> the 3. caſt the crowne from the head of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. with his foote. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3. brought the Emperour <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hilip</hi> and <hi>Otho</hi> to deſtruction. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. and <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4. furiouſly aſſaulted <hi>Frederike</hi> 2. with ſuch ſoldiers, as had made a vow to fight againſt the <hi>Saracens. Iohn 22. Benet.</hi> 12. and <hi>Clement,</hi> 6. with implacable hatred proſecuted <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> for no other reaſon, but becauſe hee tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Imperiall diadem without the Popes conſent. thus was <hi>Harold</hi> ouercome by the conqueror through the Popes curſes, and King <hi>Iohn</hi> beſides his other troubles loſt all <hi>Normandy.</hi> How did <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. infeſt both <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> attempting to ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gate <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; the houſe of <hi>Colonia</hi> and <hi>Italy?</hi> I will come no further, for euery man knowes our moderne ſtories, &amp; that the Maieſty of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath written a diſcourſe againſt this <hi>Pontificeous</hi> vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; is it not high time then to bring this man to the bar of Gods iudgement ſeate, &amp; indite him of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the glory &amp; tranſcendent power of heauen, and for this intollerable pride againſt the Princes of the earth, who are the chiefe and abſolute ſubſtitutes of God in their Kingdomes, and muſt anſwer in their ſtewardſhip for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhionable mixtures, &amp; vniuſtifiable diuiding their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, with one, that hath nothing to doe with worldly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combrances, or diſtributing inheritances, but rather ſhould be an humbled miniſter of God, &amp; a ſeruant indeed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence holy things to the people? therfore I wonder how the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſeeing, hearing, and knowing this <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian oppoſition</hi> to Gods truth and the gouernment of all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21678:22"/> Common welths can haue their hearts more hardned then ſtone (for the ſtones rent aſunder at the Paſſion of Chriſt, when the lewes laughed their ſaluation to ſcorne) and their eares ſtopped worſe then the adders with her taile, &amp; will not hearken to this Inditement, nor allow of theſe vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable proofes, &amp; vndeniable inferences. Anſwer a Gods name, yee that muſt anſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe, how comes this blockiſhnes and ſtupiditie, how, comes all this about, if the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe be deſtroyed after <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and the man of ſin reuealed, whom God will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with the breath of his noſtrels? and thus much for my ſecond Inditement.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="indictment">
                  <head>The third Inditement of Antichriſt for abuſing the people with lying miracles.</head>
                  <p>I am glad I haue done with theſe tedious relations, and wonderfull proofes againſt the vſurpation of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> becauſe I would make you glad too, and exh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lerate your ſad hearts with a modeſt mirth, which muſt needes be rayſed from theſe deuiſes of men, and lying miracles. But be not too forward, nor preiudicate againſt me in caſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the booke, as vnderualewing the ſame, as though you ſhall be acquainted with no other things then is in the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda aurea,</hi> or <hi>Doctor Sheldons</hi> diſcouery of Popiſh miracles, or common Relations whereby you may ſay I know the ſtories already, for I hope I ſhall not name one of them, yet excite laughter by relating ſuch particulars, as ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force your meditation, how the Deuill had no greater cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor preuaileable ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e then to ſupport the <hi>Romiſh</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by ſuch palpable, groſſe, filthy, and idle inuentions; or ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o better iudgment or if you will infuſed grace, then to be ſeduced with abſurditie, and impoſſibilitie, for what is there in this doctrine of Papiſtry more then in the poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fiction of the Gods, the tales of <hi>Homer, Herodatus, Ouid, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ocace</hi> and the reſt, the cunning of crafty women, and falſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21678:23"/> Prieſts and Prophets, who made an Art of morning diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, propheſying, &amp; calculating natiuities, the deceites of lying tongues, the preſumption and bragging of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters, and the ceremonies of <hi>Augurers, Pithoniſts,</hi> and <hi>Arts</hi> maſters in incantations; againſt whom the Poets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had many inuectiues, and condemned the Prieſts of that time, as we doe the Friers of this age: for which purpoſe I haue cited ſome few extracts of ſufficient authors.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heì mihi Verſipelles vt homines ſemper odi:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Euripides Ion.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>qui componentes tniuſta deinde fraudes adornant.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>In another place.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Linguae enim nulla fides, quae externa quidem</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Eurip. Hippoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Coronatus.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>concilia hominum corrigere nouit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A ſe ipſa vero plurima p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſidet mala.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>In another place.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lingua enim affectans ca, quae iniuſta, ſcit</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>probe obtegere. Nudet fraude agere.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Enrip. medea.</note>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>In another place the wicked woman takes vpon her to ſay. <note place="margin">Metamorp.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Flectere ſinequeam ſuperos, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>heronta moucbo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>In another place.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Palluit attonitus ſacris ſeralibus Aruns,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> iram ſuperum raptis quaeſiuit in extis,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Lncun. lib. 1. Pharſ.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>terruit ipſe color Vatem &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>And in another place.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>—perſtat rabies, nec cunctalocuta eſt,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>quem non emiſit ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt deus, illa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eroces</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>torquet adhuc oculos, toto<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Vagantia Caelo</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lumina nunc Vultu pauido. Nunc torua minaci</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſtat nunquam facies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ubor igneus inficit ora</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Lucen lib. 5. Pharſ.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>liuenteſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> genas, nec qui ſolet eſſe timenti</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>terribilis, ſed pallor ineſt, necfeſſa qnieſcunt</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Corda, ſed vt tumidus Boreae poſt flamina pontus</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>rauca gemit, ſic nulla leuant ſuſpiria vatem.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>And in many other places the ſelfe ſame things are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected againſt impoſturing men in what art ſoeuer, as now the true Chriſtian imputes to cooſening Monkes &amp; Friers;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21678:23"/> let the carnall Goſpeller and lukewarme profeſſor come out with <hi>piae fraudes</hi> neuer ſo much.</p>
                  <p>But to the purpoſe in hand.</p>
                  <p>They begin with <hi>Nero,</hi> whoſe bodie they will haue the <note place="margin">Nero.</note> Deuills to keepe after he had kild himſelfe, whereby great harme, beſides nocturnall terrours was done to the people; till by a Miracle of our <hi>Lord,</hi> the body was taken away, found farre of, and at laſt buried, whereby the firmament was quieted, and the fiendes departed.</p>
                  <p>They follow with a tale concerning <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian:</hi> they will <note place="margin">Veſpaſian.</note> haue Waſpes to breede in his noſe, but as ſoone as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued the hiſtory of Chriſt, or at leaſt made them beleeue his conuerſion, he was cured, and the neſt fell away like a core, or if you will a combe full of holes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Traian</hi> was a great enemy to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as by his perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions <note place="margin">Traian.</note> appeared: yet Saint <hi>Grego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> acquainted with many excellent things in his gouernment, prayed to our Lord to keepe his ſoule out of <hi>Hell;</hi> but receiuing no abſolute an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, more then a tempeſt, he left it diſputable amongſt the Doctors, whether he be ſaued, or no, as it is of <hi>Sampſon, Salomon, Origen,</hi> and others, of whom the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> diſputeth <hi>Pro &amp; Con,</hi> and as their paſſion leades them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-takes to deliuer out of <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>They tell a ſtrange tale of <hi>Fabianus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Fabianus.</note> and a martyr, who was choſen by the deſcending of a white doue vpon him, and ſaying, thou ſhalt be Pope: wherein there is ſome probabilitie: For in the life of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> it is recorded, that he made the people beleeue, that the holy Ghoſt vſed to appeare to him viſibly, and acquaint him with the ſecrets of heauen, to countenance which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, he had taught a doue indeede to come and take peaſe out of his eare, which he many times performed in the ſight of the people.</p>
                  <p>They confeſſe, that <hi>Marcelinus</hi> was Pope: yet he offred <note place="margin">Marcelinus.</note> incenſe to <hi>Idols</hi> for feare of death: but at laſt he repented, and was a martyr: notwithſtanding, for his offence his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy lay three dayes v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buried, till by a viſion of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21678:24"/> 
                     <hi>Marcelinus,</hi> it was allowed for ſufficient penance, ſo at laſt it had the ceremonies of a mortyr.</p>
                  <p>About the time that the <hi>Saxons</hi> entred into <hi>England,</hi> they haue a miracle of the ſeauen ſleepers, who were two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <note place="margin">Seauen ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> yeares in a caue, and then came abroad with ſtrange diſcoueries; the Storie is much enlarged by them with their ſeuerall names, and we haue the play: and why may not this be true, conſidering <hi>Epimenides</hi> going to ſeeke his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſheepe, tooke vp his reſting place through the heat of the day in a caue, and there ſlept fiftie yeares without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his bodie, either in conſtitution, or complexion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leo Tuſcus</hi> was a Confeſſor, Martyr, and Pope, in which <note place="margin">Leo Tuſcus.</note> time he was tempted by a woman, who would needs kiſſe him, but the holy man by no meanes conſented to ſuch immodeſtie: yet with much ſtrugling ſhee kiſſed his hand, whether he would or no, whereupon he commanded it to be cut off, becauſe no corrupt fleſh ſhould remaine about him; which when the people perceiued, they earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſed our <hi>Lady</hi> for him, and ſhee moſt mercifully reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it againe, as if a broken peece were to be cemented, and then he ſayd Maſſe as before, and acknowledged our <hi>Lady</hi> his Sauiour.</p>
                  <p>What you call the <hi>Stonendy</hi> on <hi>Salibury</hi>-plaine (being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stonendy</hi> and <hi>Merlin.</hi>
                     </note> the monument of <hi>Aurclius Ambroſe,</hi> from whom the towne of <hi>Amſbury</hi> tooke originall, and denomination) they will haue a deuiſe of <hi>Merlins,</hi> who brought them by miracle out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the hill <hi>Kian,</hi> called Giants <hi>Kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol,</hi> and ſo placed with wonderment, as you ſee them. This <hi>Merlin</hi> liued in the time of <hi>Vter Pendragon,</hi> and was as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in his actions, as his birth: he was they ſay the ſonne of a <hi>Succubus,</hi> and <hi>Incubus,</hi> and performed ſtrange things for the King: eſpecially in imitation of the ſtory of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> who in the likeneſſe of <hi>Amphitrio</hi> lay with <hi>Alcumena,</hi> and ſo begat <hi>Hercules:</hi> he tranſhapt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ter</hi> the King into the Earles figure of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and <hi>Vlfrie</hi> the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine into <hi>Iordane</hi> his man, whereby he came into the caſtle of <hi>Tintagill,</hi> and accompanied the faire <hi>Igrena,</hi> and ſo the valiant <hi>Arthur</hi> was borne.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21678:24"/>
                  <p>When S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> preached at <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">S. Auſtin.</note> and <hi>Panimes</hi> derided him, and caſt ray tailes vpon him, with the garbiſh of noyſome fiſh: whereupon he prayed to God, that the children of <hi>Kent</hi> might be borne with tailes: and ſo to the terrour of the Inhabitants, and yet conuerſion of many, it came to paſſe, as they fooliſhly beleeue.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Oſwald</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland</hi> was ſlaine by the <note place="margin">Oſwald.</note> 
                     <hi>Saxons,</hi> they cut off his head, which they buried in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of <hi>Berdnay,</hi> whereupon he was conſecrated a martyr, and our <hi>Lord</hi> for the confirmation of his ſanctitie, cauſed many miracles to be done, both by him, and for him: which wrought ſo effectually in the hearts of the people, that they were ſoone conuerted to Chriſt; and beleeued in the holy Church.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>Paſculus</hi> the Deacon <hi>Cardinall</hi> held againſt <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Paſculus.</note> with the faction of <hi>Laurentius</hi> to his death, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was put to the paines of Purgatory, and to keepe the bathes. This ſtory is from <hi>Gregory</hi> in <hi>Dialogis,</hi> who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, tht it was viſibly manifeſted to the people, who were thereby detayned in awe and obedience, and euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter feared to offend the cenſure of the Church.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall reade, that <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> had <note place="margin">Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.</note> a great contention with <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> about the two natures of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>Emperour</hi> would needes enforce him to be of his opinion: but the valiant Biſhop, moued with zeale and piet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e anſwered thus; I thought I had come to <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian Emperour,</hi> but ſure I haue found <hi>Diocleſian</hi> a perſecuting tyrant: at which wordes the <hi>Emperour</hi> fell downe on his knees, as <hi>Saul</hi> from his horſe in his iourney to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> acknowledging the power of the <hi>Church,</hi> and confeſſing, it was a miracle, for he had ſeene a ſtrange viſion.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour in the latter end of his <note place="margin">Mauritius.</note> raigne conteſted with Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> and would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his holineſſe for ſuperiour: there appeared a man of <hi>Rome</hi> vnto him, clothed in a religious habit, yet
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21678:25"/> holding a naked ſword in his hand, and thus menaced him; <hi>Thou ſhalt be deſtroyed:</hi> whereupon <hi>Phocas</hi> taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of this <hi>Viſion,</hi> or if you had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ather of a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie and coniuration againſt him, opportunely made himſelfe head of the <hi>Faction,</hi> and ſo bere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t him both of life and <hi>Empire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, ſucceeded <hi>Samianus,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly <note place="margin">Samianus.</note> traduced the ſaid <hi>Gregory</hi> for pride, and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, eſpecially that his almes and liberalitie tended to oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation. Wherevpon followed ſome diſtemperature, and oppreſſion of his beſt faculties, with a continuall ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Gregory</hi> did ſtill haunt him, and rebuke him: which ended not without a <hi>Viſion,</hi> in which he ſmote him on the head. This proued ominous, for vpon the conceit he preſently ſickned, and dyed; and ſo the <hi>Church</hi> made a ſtory of it, that it was long of the blow, which <hi>Gregory</hi> gaue him.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall reade, that the Emperour and other Princes <note place="margin">Heraclius.</note> of <hi>Europe</hi> proſpered in the recouery of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſo returned the holy Croſſe thither againe, which when <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclius</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> vnderſtood, he would needes make a iourney to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which muſt bee performed with great pride, pompe, and oſtentation. But ſee the miracle; When he came to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and thought to make his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Cittie with glorious magnificence, the gates ſhut themſelues againſt him of their owne accord, and the more violent he was to enter, the more ſtronger and cloſer they kept themſelues: till he bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of a contrary courſe, which was humiliation, and acknowledging of mercy, then did they open againe of themſelues, and he was louingly receiued of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deodans</hi> and <hi>Agatho</hi> were <hi>Popes,</hi> who healed Lepers with <note place="margin">Healing of Lepers.</note> kiſſing them; and performed many Cures without Salue, or Medicine: For ſo you reade, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did the like by impoſition of handes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21678:25"/>
                  <p>In the daies of <hi>Martine</hi> the firſt <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> you ſhall <note place="margin">Martine 1.</note> read, that his enemies conſpired his death, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſent one <hi>Spartarius</hi> of <hi>Olympus</hi> to kill him, which in the time of his ſaying of Maſſe, and ſacring the Hoſt was reuealed: but ſee the miracle! As he approached neere him, he was ſtrucke blind, whereby the <hi>Pope</hi> auoided the danger, and the Church increaſed in reputation.</p>
                  <p>The reuerend <hi>Beda</hi> became blind for age, and was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Beda.</note> mocked and ſcoffed of the people, as the children called <hi>Elias</hi> bald pate: in which time of his contempt, and deſpight, they brought him to preach to a company of ſtones; he ſuppoſing they had beene men, went forward in his exhortation, and when he had finiſhed, the ſtones ſpake vnto him, thanked him, and ſaid, <hi>Amen venerabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Beda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Carolus Martelius</hi> to ſupply his wants in the warres, <note place="margin">Carolus Martellus.</note> bereaued many <hi>Churches</hi> of their Treaſure, Chalices, and ſo impoueriſhed the Clergy, by reaſon of which intruſion and exaction, when hee died, he was viſibly carried into <hi>Hell,</hi> as they faine: to proue the truth whereof, <hi>Eucharius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aurelian,</hi> as he was at his praiers ſaw him bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule tormented in a locall place, which becauſe many doubted of, and that an Angell could not reueale ſuch a viſion, the <hi>Abbot</hi> of S. <hi>Denis</hi> would needs run to his Sepulcher, and opening the cheſt found a huge Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon in it, which leaped in his face, and made him a little afraid.</p>
                  <p>They alſo write of <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, a <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Leo 4. a Pope.</note> who going in Proceſſion to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church, was ſurpriſed by his enemies, and in reuenge they cut out both tongue and eies: yet was our <hi>Lady</hi> ſo gracious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that though he wanted the inſtruments, he had the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>culties of ſeeing and ſpeaking.</p>
                  <p>The enmity was ſo great betweene <hi>Sergius</hi> and <hi>Formo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Sergius &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſus.</note> 
                     <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that <hi>Sergius</hi> cut off his head, and threw the body into <hi>Tiber,</hi> which was yet taken vp by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Fiſher-men, and brought ſolemnly to Chriſtian bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21678:26"/> But ſee the wonder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no ſooner came it into the Church, but all the Images of the Saints bowed downe, and made it reuerence.</p>
                  <p>It is a poſition in <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> neither to diſcouer any thing <note place="margin">Benedict. 9.</note> which may tend to the diminution of the <hi>Pontifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ian</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor to reueale any thing confeſſed, nor practiſe what may proue <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> againſt the <hi>Popes</hi> holineſſe, nor in a word, neglect the ſuperſtitious care of their Church ceremonies: yet here they themſelues tell a ſtory of <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus</hi> the ninth, that hee was damned for his vitious life, and viſibly ſeene tormented in <hi>Hell:</hi> yea ſuch was the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the curſe againſt him, that after death he appeared to the terrour of many in a moſt horrible ſhape and figure, his head and taile like an Aſſe, and his body like a Lions.</p>
                  <p>All men agree to the hiſtory of <hi>Edward</hi> ſurnamed the <note place="margin">Ed. <hi>Confeſſor,</hi>
                     </note> that he was a religious <hi>Prince,</hi> and repleniſhed with thoſe excellent gifts of wiſedome, and piety; but few men can iuſtifie that this was obſerued in his life. As hee kneeled at Maſſe in the very inſtant of the eleuation of <hi>Chriſts</hi> body, he ſaw <hi>Swaine</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> drowned in the ſea with all his army, at which hee ſo ſmiled, that at laſt it tended to a laughter; whereat the company won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and were bold to demand, what the matter meant: wherupon he diſcouered the ſecret, &amp; called certaine <hi>Earles</hi> to participate of the viſion, amongſt whom the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> ſaw the Bread turne apparantly into the likeneſſe of a young child. But to adde more truth to this miracle, the hangings in the Quier a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Weſt minſter</hi> conſiſt of this ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and there you may ſee the conceit of the buſineſſe. O the ſuperſtition of thoſe daies, and palpable groſneſſe of the Clergies colluſion! This King gaue alſo his Signet for the loue of S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> to a poore man, but ſee the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full care and reſpect of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> hee ſent it him ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e againe in the belly of a fiſh, for when a goodly fiſh was preſented to the King, as the Cooke dreſſed the ſame, the Kings Seale was found in the entrailes: others tell the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this manner, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> tooke it ſo kindly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21678:26"/> now at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that he returned it backe againe by two pilgrimes, whom he poſted into <hi>England</hi> in one night for the ſame purpoſe, ſo the ring was deliuered, and Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> commendation preſented to the king.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth was <hi>Cardinall,</hi> and <hi>Legat</hi> in <hi>France</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gregory 7.</note> before he was <hi>Pope,</hi> where he ſo religiouſly proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Simoniacks,</hi> that he called diuers to account (as we ſay) <hi>in foro publico:</hi> amongſt whom a certaine <hi>Biſhop</hi> by bribing and corrupting his accuſers thought to eſcape: but <hi>Gregory</hi> knowing by reuelation the deceit, preuented it in this manner; he commanded him to ſay <hi>Gloria patri,</hi> if he had not abuſed the holy Ghoſt, which by no meanes he could doe, whereupon he was adiudged guiltie, and depriued of his Biſhopricke. But ſee the miſchiefe: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he could ſay it well enough, and made them all wonder at the alteration.</p>
                  <p>I beleeue though you haue read many <hi>Chronicles,</hi> you <note place="margin">William R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fus King.</note> yet haue not read of this ſtorie concerning the death of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> that a little before he was ſhot by Sir <hi>Walter Tirrell,</hi> he dreamed, he was let bloud, &amp; in ſo great a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, that a ſtreame of it leapt vp on high toward heauen, more than a hundred fathom, and the day was preſently darkened as the night. Againe, a Monke of his houſe drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that king <hi>William</hi> went into a Church with a great company of people, and amongſt them all he tooke the Image of the Crucifix, and moſt ſhamefully rent it with his teeth, but the Crucifix meekly ſuffred all, till like a mad man he pulled the armes off, threw it vnder feet, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vpon it in deſpight, had not a great fire come out of the Cruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fix mouth, which preuented the king from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting further outrage, and awaked the Monke. This dreame was with much adoe declared to the king, and his owne dreame with more adoe diſputed vpon, and both the dreames made a matter of fearefull prediction, ſo that the concluſion extended to caution and premonition to his Maieſtie, that there was ſure ſome misfortune immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ouer him.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21678:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> was one of the <hi>Popes</hi> champions, and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Thomas Becket.</note> traitors, of whoſe lies and miracles I am aſhamed to wrice: for they will haue him turne a Capon into a Carpe, as he was at dinner in <hi>Rome</hi> on Saint <hi>Marks</hi> day, and when he was martyred, to heale the ſicke, wounded, and luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, with the touch of his tombe and relickes: my author recounts two and twentie miracles done for his ſake.</p>
                  <p>When Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> was canonized a Saint, and <note place="margin">Saint ern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd.</note> conſecrated in his ſhrine or chappell, his <hi>Abbot</hi> forbad him to doe any more miracles, becauſe there came ſuch a concourſe of people, that he was notable to entertaine them nor willing to be ſo continually imploied: the like or much more is fathered vpon <hi>Simon de Momford Earle of Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Momford.</note> a notorious rebell againſt <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he went vnder the <hi>vmbrela</hi> of a good <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths man,</hi> and maintainer of the liberties of Church, they inuented many a lie for him, that he might preſerue his reputation after death, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Robert Bruiſe</hi> rebelled againſt <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, he was proclaimed a traitor, and after taken and beheaded, yet did they hang vp his body in chaines: but there came ſo many deuils by night to torment it with hookes, that they were faine to watch it, guard it, and make fires about the place.</p>
                  <p>I cannot but enlage the ſtorie of <hi>Thomas</hi> the good Earle <note place="margin">Sir Simond Frizell.</note> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> one of the greateſt ſubiects of the world, whom <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond moſt vnkindly put to death, and wherein they went along with his worthines, allow them the praiſes of their good report, but when they come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices and ſuperſtitious conceits, I leaue them to their owne fallacies, and cannot chooſe but laugh at their fictions: for they not onely repute him a Martyr, but diuulge that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a miracle was ſhewne by him, or done for him. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a <note place="margin">The Earle of Lancaſter.</note> Prieſt reſtored to his ſight, who had beene long blinde, by wiping his eies with the Altar cloth. A child drowned and found dead the third day in a well, was brought to his tombe, and not onely recouered by touching the defunct,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21678:27"/> but receiued life, which continued many yeeres. Diuers mad men and diſtracted women by leaning their heads only vpon his tombe, were reſtored to a temperature in their ſenſes. A rich man of <hi>Gaſcoign:</hi> halfe dead and rotten on the one ſide, ſo that you might ſee his liuer, was bleſſed by his Tombe with vnuſuall recouery: and many ſuch like miracles were performed by him, whereupon the <hi>Spencers</hi> both prohibited the concourſe of people, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to his <hi>Chappell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could name the reſt, but theſe as the reſt are the durty waters from a corrupt and puddled channell, and muſt both diſcouer the impiety of ſuch a profeſſion, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of ſuch <hi>Prieſts</hi> that will hang gew gawes and groſſe deuices about the necke of religion, to make her ſeeme more gawdy, and a very puppet in the world: yet ſuch was the pleaſure of diuine <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to permit the Deuill to put on a cloake of ſanctity to deceiue whole multitudes who were ſubiect to vanity: ſuch the coherence of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that <hi>Papiſtry</hi> ſhould haue her <hi>Progreſſe,</hi> as you haue heard: and ſuch was the deceit of men, that they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in ignorance, becauſe they delighted in ceremonies rather than ſubſtance, in painted deuices and outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, rather than inward or ſpirituall worſhipping of God, in fooleries to pleaſe the naturall man, rather than ſenſeleſſe kneeling in vaine to the aire (as they would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it) when men ſee no pourtraiture nor reſemblance, and yet the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw no image. Thus was ſinne not onely multiplied in the world, but men for the hardneſſe of their hearts detained in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuperſtition: thus theſe miſeries fell vpon them for denying and abuſing that purity of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> eſtabliſhed in the Primitiue Church, and thus God would be glorified in reſeruing ſtill a Church to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and opening the eies of humbled ſoules, to ſee the paths of their ſaluation according to the praier of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Father I thanke thee that thou haſt reuealed thy will to babes and ſilly men, when the mighty, rich, and full were
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21678:28"/> ſent empty away, and the proud boaſters of learning and knowledge excluded. But if you would bee acquainted with a wonder indeed, and ſee a miracle, obſerue how this ſmall graine of muſtard ſeed, this handfull of Gods people, theſe deſpiſed creatures, this poore Church, this derided profeſſion did in the end proue a flouriſhing tree, an Vniuerſall Congregation, a magnified people, a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Monarchy, a glorified compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo that (as you haue heard) the Kings of the earth haue laid downe their crownes before ſimple Preachers, who haue but come with the eccho of <hi>Chriſts</hi> voice: the Angells in heauen therefore ſing <hi>Hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>luiahs,</hi> and the God of all hath a ſtone ready in his hand to ſtrike <hi>Babel</hi> to confuſion. Anſwer then a Gods name, you that muſt anſwer before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Throne of the Lambe: how comes this about, if the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is diſcouered, and thus arraigned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, and the man of ſinne reucaled by theſe lying mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, whom God will conſume with the breath of his noſtrils.</p>
                  <p>But before I doe <hi>in arenam deſcendere,</hi> and play my <hi>Maſters</hi> priſe indeed, that is, ſtrike all dead with the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Gods iudgement againſt thoſe that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <note place="margin">Iſaiah 55.</note> to the pure waters of life, and hearken to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> who bids them come and buy without money; I haue a little more to ſay, and ſome remainder of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer account to make vp.</p>
                  <p>They talke of a great battell againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> who <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1457</label> were ouercome by miracle: for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter ſome exorciſme of holy men, the <hi>Turkes</hi> fled crying, that a great army of Knights followed them, who ſeemed ſouldiers, but were indeed Angels. And why might not this bee done, as well as <hi>Eliſha</hi> to ſhew his ſeruant a multitude of chario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, <note place="margin">2 Kings.</note> and horſes, ſo that there was more with them, than againſt them.</p>
                  <p>They will haue a ſtone in <hi>Angleſey</hi> of that property, <note place="margin">Angleſey.</note> that how farre ſoeuer a man carries it in the day, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21678:28"/> of it ſelfe at night into the <hi>Iland:</hi> for triall where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Hugh</hi> of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, bound it to another huge ſtone with iron chaines, and threw them into a deepe water, but in the morning the ſtone was found in <hi>Angleſey</hi> againe: afterward a Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le faſtened it to his owne leg, but his thigh rotted, and the ſtone went away.</p>
                  <p>In the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gus</hi> king of <note place="margin">The Picts and Sam. Andrew.</note> 
                     <hi>Picts</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> infeſted a great part of <hi>Brittanic,</hi> till at laſt they were beſet with a formidable armie, and thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be deſtroyed: but Saint <hi>Andrew</hi> taking pittie vpon him, comforted him, and aſſured the victorie, if he would giue the third part of the land to the Church, which he ſolemnly ratified: ſo a croſſe was aduanced in honour of Saint <hi>Andrew,</hi> and the armie marching forward with the Standard, the <hi>Brittons</hi> were amazed at ſuch an vnlooked for returne and recouerie of their enemies, and the <hi>Picts</hi> moſt fortunatly preuailed.</p>
                  <p>I will not tell you, though my author doth, that <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Saint Patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t and Ireland.</note> had as many venomous creatures, and noyſome ſnakes, as other countries, vntill <hi>ſanctus Patricius</hi> chaſed them away with his ſtaffe: nor of their witches, which were turned into Hares, becauſe they be common tales with ſot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſh, ignorant, and ſuperſtitious people, both in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Theſſaly, Norway,</hi> and other countries: yea of mine owne knowledge in the <hi>Ilands</hi> of the Arches, the tale of <hi>Lucius Appuleius,</hi> or the golden Aſſe, is beleeued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a truth. But this I will be bold to ſay, that the life of Saint <hi>Patrike</hi> is wel written in a good Latine phraſe, and dedicated to that euer memorable Earle and worthy pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of hoſpitalitie and honorable behauiour, the Earle of <hi>Clenricard:</hi> wherein are ſuch ſtrange things, and of that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, that neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt</hi> came neere him for actiue imployment, if without pietie we may belecue that ſtorie. As for S. <hi>Patriks Purgatorie,</hi> or the great lake of <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> as incredible things are reported of them, as of Saint <hi>Patrike</hi> himſelfe. The ſtorie is thus enlarged: A woman
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21678:29"/> drawing or taking water out of a wel, and hearing her child crie, run to it for haſte, and forgat to couer the ſame, which in the meane while ſwelled ouer ſo immeaſurably, that it drowned all the countrey, but the maine reaſon was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the people were <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and God thus ſent his vengeance vpon them.</p>
                  <p>In the ſixth yeere of the reigne of <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth, <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>roope Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſhop of Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke.</note> 
                     <hi>Scroope</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> was executed for treaſon. He deſired the hangman to giue him fiue ſtrokes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſts 5. wounds, which he performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: whereupon at the ſame inſtant, the king ſitting at dinner had fiue ſtrokes on the necke by a perſon inuiſible, after which he proued a leper, for recouery whereof he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined a iourney to <hi>Icruſalem,</hi> but was preuented by ſicknes, though his treaſure &amp; furniture of his houſes were ſhipped, and ſo he died in the Abbey of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in a chamber called <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> many ſtrange miracles were performed for this Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 36. of <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, a Prieſt did pronounce at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, and there confeſſed in publike, that he himſelfe ſaying Maſſe pricked his finger and be-bloudied <note place="margin">Alying Prieſt.</note> the <hi>Corporas</hi> with the Altar clothes, purpoſing to make the people beleeue, that the hoſt had bled miraculouſly, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As it was in the time of <hi>Henrie</hi> the 6. about <hi>Ioan la pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil de dieu</hi> at <hi>Orleans,</hi> who was afterwards burnt for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſturing whore, by the Duke of <hi>Bedford</hi> at <hi>Roan:</hi> ſo fell it out with <hi>Elizabeth Barton</hi> a Nun, &amp; holy Maid of <hi>Kent,</hi> whoſe miraculous lies are rather fearefull than ridiculous: <note place="margin">Holy mai of Kent.</note> for ſhe not onely deceiued the Biſhops, but brought her ſelfe with ten other to a lamentable <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi> Looke <hi>Hall, Grafton,</hi> and diuers Chronicles.</p>
                  <p>I am almoſt wearie with wearying you in the diſcourſe of theſe fopperies, but ſhould wearie you and torment my ſelfe altogether to relate the like of other countries, not packed vp (as I told you before) in the <hi>Legenda Aurea,</hi> or <hi>Nauclerus,</hi> or <hi>Coſterus,</hi> or other ſufficient authours, who haue for the ſame purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raduced theſe wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21678:29"/> and papiſticall couſening Prieſts, or if you will, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiarie <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> who ſtill run at randome to ſeduce ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people, and confound weake and eaſie beleeuing ſoules. Therefore I deſiſt from further diſturbance, and onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thus much from a poore afflicted ſpirit, and euery way vnfortunate man, (as we now in theſe times profanely abuſe that Character) to tender your owne ſaluation by conſidering what a ſtrange religion this is, and aboue all other in the world, agreeing and concurring with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> eſpecially in this point of ſignes, and wonders, and lying miracles, ſo that if this fall to my ſhare, that am the meaneſt of a thouſand, what can others doe, that haue <hi>Beniamins</hi> portion fiue times doubled: both concerning Scripture, Hiſtorie, Fathers, Knowledge, Iudgement, Eloquution, and other faculties. As for ſuch as are yet willing to be deceiued, and hauing heard of that great dutie of perſeuerance in holy matters, peruert it to obſtinacie and pertinacitie in idolatrous ſuperſtition, I ſay no more, but anſwer a Gods name you that muſt anſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe; How comes this about? if the Papacy ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe be deſtroyed, ſeeing <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is diſcouered and thus arraigned and indited, the man of ſinne reuealed by theſe lying miracles, whom God will conſume with the breath of his noſtrils. And thus much for his indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: now to his puniſhment and vtter extirpation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Section III. <hi>Or the execution of Antichriſt according to the ſentence of condemnation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Might haue begun this diſcourſe with that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, but I hope it comes now in order well enough. <note place="margin">Note the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</note> Obſerue then I pray you the Simile. Politicke ſtates and well gouerned Commonwealths, haue either commonly ſecret intelligencers, or publicke Ambaſſadors in forren
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21678:30"/> countries to acquaint them with all occurrences, and ſo let nothing paſſe, no not triuiall accidents, which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the good of their countrie, without reuealing: ſo that if letters or certificat of credit come, that there are Iurking amongſt vs certaine traitors, that intend the ruine of the kingdome, and endanger the life of the Prince, there is preſently ſearch in euery corner, and warrants ſent out to apprehend them: afterward vpon happy diſcouery and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt attachment, they are impriſoned and kept ſecure, till they may be further examined: then vpon due and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceedings they are to be arraigned and indited of high treaſon, as they are found and proued delinquents <hi>in Crimino laſe Maieſtatis:</hi> Laſt of all, vpon finding <hi>Billa vera</hi> and iuſtifiable conuiction, the ſentence of condemnation goes out, and they are executed accordingly: ſo hath the holy Ghoſt dealt with the Church of God concerning the traitors of mens ſoules, and diſcouery of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the inſtrument of Satan to bring vs to damnation: he hath firſt made vs acquainted that there is ſuch a Viper lurking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let no man deceiue you by any meanes: For that day ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſ. 2. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>not come, except there come a falling away firſt, and that man of ſinne be reuealed, the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nne of perdition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelfe aboue all, that is called</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>God, or that is worſhipped: ſo that he as God ſitteth in the temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe, that he is God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember ye not that when I was yet with you I told you</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I haue not written vnto you, becauſe you know not the truth:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Epiſt. Iohn 2. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>but becauſe you know it, and that no lie is of the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is a lier, but he that denieth, that Ieſus is the Chriſt:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>22</label> 
                  <hi>he is Antichriſt, that denieth the Father, and the Sonne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And euerie ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Ieſus Chriſt is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chap 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>come in the fleſh, is not of God, and that is that ſpirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, whereof you haue heard, that it ſhould come, and euen now already is it in the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you ſee what a noble intelligencer and friend from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21678:30"/> heauen we haue had to acquaint the Church of God, that the betraier of mens ſoules, and traiters to the maieſty of God are euery where lurking amongſt vs, vpon which certificate I, though vnworthy, and the meaneſt of Gods ſeruants, haue aduentured to ſearch and find him out, and vpon the ſearch haue not onely diſcouered, and reuealed him, but arraigned and indited him, ſo that I hope no man can miſlike or traduce this iuſtifiable proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, which if they dare doe, what will they then ſay to the ſentence of condemnation, which is now to be denounced from God himſelfe, and the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>Sibylls,</hi> ancient Fathers, and their women Saints: ſure, ſure, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> will fret and rage, imagining vaine <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. Acts.</note> things: and I anſwer with <hi>Paul,</hi> after the way you call he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, I ſerue the God of my Fathers: and with <hi>Iob,</hi> though thou kill me (O Lord) I will not forſake thee. But to the purpoſe in hand.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Antichriſts puniſhment from Scripture.</head>
                  <p>IF you ſearch the <hi>Prophets,</hi> you ſhall finde, that hee that drowned the world, burnt <hi>Sodome</hi> to ſinders, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed <hi>Pharao</hi> with whole mountaines of waters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded <hi>Aegypt,</hi> deſtroied <hi>Tirus,</hi> who was as proud and <note place="margin">Iſaiah 19. 23. 34 46 Ezech. 25. 1. Damel and the reſt of the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> exalted as euer <hi>Rome</hi> in her firſt and ſecond glory, reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the cauſe of his Church, ouerthrew the idols of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> a meere figure of <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Prelacy: threatned and diſſipated <hi>Ammon, Moab, Edom,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and in a word all the mighty Monarchies vnder the Sun, reſembled to fierce and cruell beaſts, ſtrange images and figures, Eagles, Rams, Goats and ſuch like <hi>Hierogliphicks.</hi> Why then ſhould any queſtion be made of the <hi>Popes</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, or <hi>Romes</hi> perpetuity? conſidering her ſinnes cry to heauen for vengeance, and her abominations are ſpred like a carpet, to the loathing of all honeſt beholders, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21678:31"/> godly <hi>Chriſtian Spectators:</hi> but to put all out of doubt, harke what the holy Ghoſt ſaith in the Reuelation, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> and city of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> is perſonated by the prediction, I referre you to all the ancient Fathers, and moderne Writers, eſpecially <hi>Tremelius, Innius, Napier,</hi> and diuers others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the reſt of the men which were not killed by theſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 9. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>plagues, yet repented not of the works of their hands, that they ſhould not worſhip Deuills, and idols of gold, and ſiluer, and braſſe, and ſtone, and of wood, which neither can ſee, nor heare, nor walke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neither repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ted they of their murders, nor of their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 21.</note> 
                     <hi>nor of their fornications, nor of their thefts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And when they ſhall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e finiſhed their teſtimony, the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 11. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſſe pit ſhall make warre againſt them, and ſhall ouercome them, and kill them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the great Dragon was caſt out, that old Serpent cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 12. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>the Deuill, and Sathan, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there followed another Angell ſaying, Babylon is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>fallen, is fallen, that great city, becauſe ſhee made all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons drinke of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Angell t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ruſt in his ſickle into the earth, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>the Vine of the earth, and caſt it into the great wine preſſe of the wrath of God, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Beaſt that thou ſaweſt, was, and is not, and ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 17. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>out of the bottomleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pit, and goe into perdition, and they that dwell on the earth ſhall wonder (whoſe names were not written in the booke of life from the foundation of the world) when they behold the Beaſt, that was, and is not, and yet is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he cried mightily with a ſtrong voice, ſaying, Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> reade the whole Chapter.</note> 
                     <hi>the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Deuils, and the bold of euery foule ſpirit, and a cage of euery vncleane and hatefull bird.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Merchants of theſe things, which were made rich</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 15.</note> 
                     <hi>by her, ſhall ſtand afarre off for the feare of her torment, weeping and wailing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21678:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſaying, alas, alas, that great city, that was clothed</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 18. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>in fine linnen, and purple, and ſcarlet, and decked with gold, and pretious ſtones, and pearles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For in one houre ſo great riches is come to nought, and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 17.</note> 
                     <hi>euery Ship-maſter, and all the company in ſhips, and Sailers, and as many as trade by ſea ſtood afarre off.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And cried, when they ſaw the ſmoake of her burning,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 18.</note> 
                     <hi>what city is like vnto this great city, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come and gather your ſelues together vnto the Supper</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 19. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>of the great God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ee may eat the fleſh of Kings, and the fleſh of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſe 18.</note> 
                     <hi>and the fleſh of mighty men, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh read more, read more, read all for Gods ſake your ſelues, and remember, that hee that writ this prediction and Propheſie, did not liue 500. yeeres after the <hi>Aſſirians Babylons</hi> deſtruction, and therefore it could not meane that which was paſt, but muſt queſtionleſſe haue relation to ſomething to come, ſo that theſe ſeuerall deſcriptions, and other fearefull propheſies can aime at nothing, but new <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> ſupremacy of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the filthy abomination of ſuch an abſurd religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo that a man would wonder at their daring confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to continue in ſuch exorbitant courſes of falſity, and filthines, when the end will be the trembling of Chriſtian hearts at the terrour of the iudgements to be denounced. In the meane while who can be ſo infatuated to beleeue, that true Religion will ſuffer her ſelfe to be beſpotted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durtied, and deformed with the filthy corruptions of mens inuentions, and idle, fooliſh, and ridiculous trumperies of colluding popiſh Prelates: and ſo I leaue the honeſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to that Spirit, which ſhall be operatiue in them to worke their conuerſion, or confirme their calling, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſee one way a ſtranger warre betweene <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> than the <hi>Gigantomachia,</hi> wherein <hi>Typhaeus</hi> and his brethren tooke vp mountaines in their hands to throw againſt <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and another way haue more cauſe of laughter, than euer <hi>Democritus</hi> had at <hi>Epictetus</hi> deforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21678:32"/> of the world, when he couered it with a coxcombe, and ſet the globe on the table to be derided by the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers: as for the obſtinate Papiſts, I ſay no more, but anſwer a Gods name you that muſt anſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe, what ſay you to this fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence of terror and puniſhments from Gods owne mouth? or what euaſion can there be to auoid the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſeeing the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> was written of purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notate the ſtate of the Church from Chriſt to the end of the world?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Antichriſts puniſhment and Romes deſtruction from the Sibyls.</head>
                  <p>ALthough the Scriptures were ſufficient according to <note place="margin">You muſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke the whole b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie of the Sibyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ecke and La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ne.</note> the former texts in the Reuelation, and many others in the Prophets, Apoſtles, and bookes of God, to declare his will and denounce his iudgements, and ſo there were no more diſputing on the authoritie and infallibilitie of the ſame: yet becauſe the naturall man is tranſported with ſhewes and ceremonies rather than ſubſtance, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting humours are ſeldome pacified without varietie, or noueltie: I claſpe once againe the bookes of holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſeale vp the Prophecies of Scripture, leſt ſome call for an interpreter, and ſtill cry out, the mother Church muſt be the interpreter of theſe myſteries; and ſpread you a carpet of ſuch Prophecies, that no man ſhall traduce their credit and renowne, nor the obſtinate and refractarie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt oppoſe their valuation: for though he could with the prophane Atheiſt and irreligious foole deny there <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> were a God, yet ſhall he confeſſe, that former times haue been like vberant ſprings to ſend forth flowing ſtreams of truth into the world, ſo that now he muſt needs be afrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in drawing ſo neere the time, wherein theſe predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are likely to be conſummated, as perſonating <hi>Rome</hi> that citie of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italie,</hi> and hunting the Pope and his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21678:32"/> Cardinals with full crie into the deſart of deſolation, and fatall confuſion.</p>
                  <p>I will then begin with the <hi>Sibyls,</hi> but both my begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ending with them and others ſhal be but a kinde of Epitomiſing, referring you to the larger volumes, with whom I onely play, as the dogs with the water of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lus,</hi> lap as they run, and dare not tarry to drinke for feare of the <hi>Crocadiles.</hi> In the ſecond booke of the Oracles of the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byls</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 2 Oraculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n Sibyl.</note> you ſhall finde it thus: <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>minum cum denique ſaeclum, &amp;c.</hi> In the tenth age of the world, the imagerie of <hi>Rome</hi> raiſed on her ſeuen hills ſhall extinguiſh the loue of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for which her ſtrength ſhall faile, and the people tremble, when they ſhall ſee her power beaten downe, and her riches taken away, yea her citie conſumed with fire through the wrath of God.</p>
                  <p>In the fifth booke it beginneth thus: <hi>De coelo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niet ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib 5.</note> As a great ſtarre fell from heauen into the ſea, and burnt vp the third part of the ſame with the creatures, ſo ſhall <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Italie</hi> be deſtroyed, that hath murthered the Saints, and troden the truth of Gods word vnder feet, that hath delighted in poiſoning, whoredome, and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; that hath nouriſhed buggerie againſt nature, that hath beene a towne of eaſe and filthineſſe, wicked, vniuſt, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt the <hi>Latines,</hi> and vnworthy of the ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le ſhe aſſumed, ſhe ſhall therefore ſit as a widow, mourning &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, as a viper fell and venomous: and the floud <hi>Tiber</hi> ſhall weepe for his ſpouſe, becauſe of her deſtruction, that was ſo mad, when her heart burned for bloud. She miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted Gods minde, and boaſted that ſhe was onely of the earth to be exalted. Therefore ſhall God ruine her, and there ſhall be no memory of her exaltation, yea ſhe ſhall be throwne downe into hell, and conſumed with euerlaſting fire.</p>
                  <p>In another place of the ſaid fifth booke it beginneth <note place="margin">Italia infoelix.</note> thus: <hi>Italia infoelix.</hi> O curſed and vnhappy <hi>Italie!</hi> thou ſhalt be made as barren as a wilderneſſe, and no man ſhall pittie thy deſolation: for thou haſt beene a murtherer of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21678:33"/> mothers, and haſt hands and hearts polluted with fllthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, buggering of boies, and lying with beaſts, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of women, and mingling inceſtuous bloud: yea thou haſt made Kings and Emperours prophane God by taking an oath to deſtroy the Saints, with a great deale more. But O God! that this ſhould be ſo long told be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, and yet all the world imitated the lewes in the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> though the king cut the rowle which <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ierem.</note> writ, in peeces, and burnt it in the fire, yet no man trembled, nor rent his clothes for feare, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In the ſeuenth booke it beginneth thus: <hi>Roma ferox</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>animi.</hi> Ambitious <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall after the <hi>Grecian</hi> manner ſtellifie her ſelfe to heauen, but when ſhe is in her greateſt exaltation, God ſhall deiect her, and caſt her vnder his feet like rubbiſh: for there ſhall come a firſt and a ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this great citie. The firſt you know is paſt by the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andals,</hi> the ſecond is to come by them, whom God hath appointed.</p>
                  <p>In the eight booke the beginning is thus: <note place="margin">Lib. 8.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Par tibi de coelo ſublim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s vertice Roma.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the meaning of the reſt is thus: that as <hi>Rome</hi> hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced it ſelfe aboue the world to heauen: ſo ſhall it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected and ruined, burnt to cinders and conſumed to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſhe ſhall be baniſhed farre off, and be bereaued of her wealth, within her walls ſhall Wolues and Serpents remaine, ſhe ſhall lie waſted, as though ſhe had neuer been: her Oracles ſhall ceaſe, and her golden gods be put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; there ſhall be no more conſultation with her idols, and it ſhall profit her nothing, that ſhe kept correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the former Senate about the multiplicitie of gods: for as they maintained the Oracles, and <hi>Statuas</hi> of <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Rhemus, Romulus,</hi> &amp;c. So doe they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the adoration and images of our Ladie, <hi>Peter, Iohn,</hi> and a thouſand other Saints for all actions, occaſions, and infirmities.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame booke followeth immediatly the explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">The Pope ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</note> of the <hi>Popes</hi> Character, and deciphering of his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21678:33"/> and conditions tending to this purpoſe, that after fifteene <hi>Emperours,</hi> of whom the laſt was <hi>Adrianus,</hi> ſhould ariſe a mighty <hi>Potentate</hi> with many crownes, whoſe name ſhall come neere vnto <hi>Ponti:</hi> which although they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret by the ſame <hi>Adrianus</hi> and <hi>Pontus, quaſi Adriaticus Pontus,</hi> now <hi>Golpho Venetiano:</hi> yet queſtionleſſe the <hi>Sibyll</hi> meant, as in other Authors imitating her is enlarged, that that <hi>Ponti</hi> had reference to <hi>Pontifex,</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould bee that <hi>Summus Pontifex,</hi> whoſe triple crowne is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and hath myſtery in the <hi>etymologie.</hi> For thus the <hi>Sibyll</hi> goes on and expreſſeth her ſelfe; That he ſhall <note place="margin">The Popes crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e and pride.</note> ſet his foot on the world, and the necks of <hi>Emperours</hi> and Kings: he ſhall receiue great gifts and bribes: he ſhall heape vp treaſures of gold, and gather together exceeding wealth: he ſhall pardon ſinnes diſcouered by confeſſion: he ſhall be skilfull in <hi>Negromancy,</hi> and ſcoffe at God in his brauery, which of late <hi>Platina</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> owne Secretary relateth, and many other Authors (as you haue read in the former Section, of diſcouery) recite as many ſtrange and blaſphemous impieties of them: and he ſhall iuſtifie errours and impiety againſt true Religion, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But then, ſaith our <hi>Sibyll,</hi> approacheth his downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall, then comes a time of mourning and heauineſſe, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting and excruciation of ſoule: he ſhall hang himſelfe for deſperation.</p>
                  <p>Here the carnall Goſpeller himſelfe makes a ſtop at <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as if it onely had relation to one man, or the laſt <hi>Pope</hi> of all, which ſhall make ſuch a tragicall end, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing his people, ſeat, and towne vtterly raſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, and not to meane the chaire of <hi>Peter</hi> or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Cardinals:</hi> but I leaue further diſceptation, and will tell you the words of the <hi>Prophecy.</hi> Alas, ſhall the people ſay, wee euer feared this deſolation, and ſo both old and young ſhall mourne for the dolorous deſtiny, yea ſit vpon the banke of <hi>Tybur</hi> ſadly lamenting the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the miſery. The <hi>Sibyll</hi> hath not yet done, but goeth ſtill forward. You ſhall vex and torment your ſelues to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21678:34"/> diſrobed of purple weeds, and Imperiall raiment, ſitting ſorrowfull and deiected in ſackcloth, and ruminating a pittifull ditty to this purpoſe: O <hi>Rome!</hi> that waſt the beauty of <hi>Latium,</hi> exalted aboue <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Peeres,</hi> thy pompe and pride ſhall beruined and neuer recouer, thou ſhalt bee trod downe and neuer riſe againe. The Eagle that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth before the armies, ſhall bee vnplumed, and no countrey ſhall bee able to releeue thee: For they ſhall all caſt off thy yoke, and be no more affrighted with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude: but if your read the reſt, you ſhall find a great deale more againſt <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then in the end ſhe concludeth thus: After this ſhall follow the diſſolution of the world, and God ſhall come to iudge the inhabitants of the earth: But firſt ſhall <hi>Rome</hi> feele the vengeance of his wrath, and a bloudy time ſhall happen to the rude people and tyrannous countrey: For ſhe forgat, how poore and bare ſhee began, and therefore muſt needs returne to the ſame priſtinate nakedneſſe, but with ſorer vengeance, and before a more dreadfull Iudge. And thus much for the <hi>Sibylls.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Antichriſts puniſhment and Romes deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <hi>ction, from certaine Fathers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NOw I appeale to the moſt obſtinate <hi>Papiſt,</hi> if theſe things are ſo long agoe written, and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically approued by many <hi>Claſſicke</hi> Authors, who haue done with the bookes of the <hi>Sibylls</hi> both in <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine,</hi> as <hi>Alexander</hi> did with <hi>Homers Iliads,</hi> lay it euery night vnder his pillow: What can they ſay but to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Authors, as if it were ſome inuention of malice, when yet they were diuulged long before <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or ſome tricke of obſeruation, as being foiſted in ſince religion was variated in the world? What can they conceiue, but there needs be ſome fire where there is ſo great a ſmoake? What can they imagine, but that theſe Prophecies tend to this
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21678:34"/> iſſue; Either ſhall the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt thriue in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> as the reformation is begun; or Papiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie muſt needs be ouer throwne, the Pope diſcredited, or the citie of <hi>Rome</hi> deſtroied, and then he may flie to <hi>Auignion</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> as he did once for 60. yeeres together. But becauſe I will haue ſome things vnanſwerable, I haue collected alſo ſome few predictions out of other Fathers, of whoſe ſufficiencie I neither meane to diſpute, nor draw forth their writings to the greateſt length, but tie my ſelfe to a ſober beleefe of their veritie, and modeſt extraction of their principles: only I muſt aduertiſe you that are readers thus farre, that they are Saints of the Popes owne canonizing, or religious men Catalogued for ſoundneſſe of iudgement, or ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of life, ſo that our Papiſts may be quickly put off from their common ſpeeches of, It is a deuice of ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke, a conceit of ſome hot braine, an inuention of diſcontented and penurious men, or ſome fooliſh tricke or other foiſted in to diminiſh the glorie of the Church, with ſuch like. And ſo to my buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>The Viſions of <hi>S. Hermas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Philippi</hi> tend all to <note place="margin">Saint Herma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> this purpoſe, that the Catholike Church ſhall by degrees fall into diuers deformities and corruptions, farre from her primitiue integritie and virginall puritie, for which ſhe ſhould vndergoe great vengeance and puniſhment, yea ſuffer a preſſure that ſhall cruſh her to peeces, and lie vnder a furie that ſhall laſh her ſides, and throw fire into the walls of that citie, which needeth purging, and was ſo ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, proud, and prophane.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt the predictions or prophecies of <hi>S. Methodius</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">St. Methodius.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Tirus,</hi> he foretelleth, that the Clergie ſhall in a manner burne vp and deſtroy the holy things of God, yea trample the ſacred Scriptures vnder feet, to aduance and ſet vp their owne inuentions, not leauing vnnamed cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, cuſtomes, and traditions. Yea he threatneth a neighbour King for taking part with the whore of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> which alſo a <hi>Franceſian</hi> Frier <hi>Philippus Boskierus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, and <hi>Bartholomeus de la Caſas a Spaniſh</hi> Biſhop re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21678:35"/> to King <hi>'Philip.</hi> Yet ſuch is the corruption of time, and power of the Inquiſition, that theſe bookes muſt not be talkt of: and to publiſh them for Gods glory, and propagation of true Religion, is among them hereſie, and a matter of difficulty, or weakening of policy.</p>
                  <p>In the library of Saint <hi>Victor</hi> at <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſome 600. yeeres <note place="margin">Saint Victor.</note> ſince there was a prediction beginning thus; <hi>Vae tibi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitas Septicollis:</hi> and proceedeth thus, that the letter K. ſhall threaren the walles of <hi>Rome,</hi> and then ſhall woe bee to the city of bloud, full of lying, falſhood, and violence. For the fall and deſtruction of the mighty men is at hand, the voice of ſcourges, wheeles and warres ſhall make her to tremble, the colour of the gold ſhall be darkned, and changed, with diuers ſuch paſſages of wonderment and obſeruation.</p>
                  <p>If you looke into the predictions, that were found in <note place="margin">Palace of Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dome.</note> the palace of Wiſedome at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, you ſhall finde it thus:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>—Caeſar regnabit vbique,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sed quo tunc vani ceſſabit gloria cleri.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>With a ſtrange inuectiue, fearefull, effectuall, prodigious, and full of matter, abſolutely againſt the preſent gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of Church and Commonwealth: ſo that a man would wonder, that ſome <hi>Herculean Pontifician</hi> arme (as he did ſtrangle the ſerpents in the cradle) did not at their firſt diſcouery thrattle and ſuppreſſe them, or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw their authoritie, when they began to take vp roome againſt <hi>Rome</hi> in mens hearts and apprehenſions: but ſuch is the will of God, and wonderfulneſſe of his power and prouidence, that both the Scriptures themſelues, and other writings, ſauoring the ſweetneſſe of their taſte, haue beene preſerued in deſpight of Tyrants, Iewes, Turkes, Infidels, Fire, Sword, and the Deuill himſelfe, and proſpered the more, when the attempts of corrupted men would either diſcredit, or ſuppreſſe the truth. For looke as in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>ſanguis martyrum</hi> proued <hi>ſemen Eccleſia,</hi> ſo in theſe prohibitions, according to the Prouerbe, men did euez
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21678:35"/> repute it a thing worthy their endeuours, ſearches, and knowledge, when it was rare to be gotten, or perillous to be diſputed vpon.</p>
                  <p>If you reade the Prophecie of Saint <hi>Scuerus</hi> Archbiſhop <note place="margin">Saint Scuerus.</note> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> you ſhall finde it thus: Woe vnto thee thou citie of the Gentiles, thou citie of riches, thou citie of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. Woe vnto thee <hi>Lombardie,</hi> for thy towers of ioy ſhall be broken downe, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cataldus Fimus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Trent</hi> hath a very rare Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie <note place="margin">Cataldus Fimus</note> accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng to the letter. When <hi>Rome</hi> beginneth to heare the loud bellowing of the fat Cow, <hi>Italie</hi> ſhall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh with diſſention and ciuill warres: for there ſhall be great emulation and hatred betweene the winged ſerpent or Dragon, and the lilly bearing Lion, with much other ſuch ſtuffe. But then he followes: Alas, Alas, weepe thou vnhappy <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the daies of affliction ſhall come vpon thee, and like ripened corne thou muſt ſuffer a threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thine in quitie. Kings from the foure corners of the earth ſhall riſe againſt thee, and thou ſhalt be brought downe for preſuming to ſit ſo high, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>In a Prophecie of Saint <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incent</hi> a <hi>Dominican</hi> Frier, the <note place="margin">Saint Vincent.</note> Church of God is compared to the foure ages of the world, Gold, Siluer, Braſſe, and Iron, ſpeaking of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church and Prelates full of Pride, Vanitie, Pompe, Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Auarice, and Luxurie, concluding with that monſtrous vice of Simonie, to which not long after the learned Monke <hi>Baptiſta Mantuanus</hi> alluded in many inuectiues, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>—Venalianobis</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">Mantuan.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Templa, ſacerdotes, altaria, ſacra, coronae,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ignis, thura, preces, calum eſt venale, Deuſque.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>You haue likewiſe Prophecies of <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> the Hermit, <note place="margin">Teleſphorus. Cataldus. Amatus. Gamalio.</note> Saint <hi>Cataldus, Ioannes Amatus,</hi> and <hi>Gamalio,</hi> inſerted in an Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth, and all concerning the wicked liues of the Prieſts, the enormities of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, the deſtruction of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the ouerthrow of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie. But if you looke into the expoſition of the 17. of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21678:36"/> 
                     <hi>Ieremie</hi> by <hi>Ioaehimus</hi> the Abbot, you ſhall finde there that <note place="margin">The Abbot Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>him.</note> the <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Germanie</hi> ſhall depart from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the ſaid Church with the Colledge of Cardinals ſhould be deſtroyed: yea this <hi>Ioaehim</hi> out of the Oracle of <hi>Sibyll Erithea</hi> foretelleth, that God will ſtirre vp the haughtie <hi>Germans</hi> againſt the Church, becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergie truſted more to the <note place="margin">Ierem. 17. 5.</note> power of man, than of God, therefore ſhall the ſhip of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> be toſſed and troubled with hoſtile incurſions and terrible aſſaults, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If you ouer-looke the Prophecies of <hi>Ioannes Lichten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Germany againſt Rome.</note> and <hi>Reynardus Lollerus,</hi> you ſhall finde that the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> ſhall make a league with <hi>France,</hi> by vertue whereof the Church ſhall be brought to beare the Croſſe with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and tribulation vpon her owne backe.</p>
                  <p>In the Oracle of <hi>Caſſandra</hi> the <hi>Sibyll Tiburtina</hi> colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <note place="margin">Sibyll Caſſandra.</note> by <hi>Godfridus Viterbienſis,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſta Nazarus,</hi> you haue a prediction, that by the valour and power of certaine <hi>German</hi> Princes, whoſe names ſhould begin with H. and P. <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be deſtroied, and <hi>Iohannes. Wolphius</hi> in his ſixteenth <hi>Centenary</hi> alledgeth, that <hi>Hydaſpes</hi> an ancient <note place="margin">Hydaſpes.</note> King of the <hi>Medes</hi> did foretell the lamentable deſolation of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; ſubuerſion both of their greatnes, and ſuperſtition.</p>
                  <p>In the yeere 1593. <hi>Petrus Paulus</hi> an Abbot of <hi>Calabria,</hi> caſting downe an old wall in his Monaſtery, found a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of ſtone by digging deepe to lay a new foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein was a corps almoſt conſumed, holding in his hand a plate of ſiluer with this inſcription; This is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Abbot of <hi>Werde</hi> of <hi>Hydrantum</hi> buried the 17. <note place="margin">Abbot of Werde.</note> of October 1279. and ſaying thus, <hi>Cum ſancta ciuitas fulgebit ſplendore none ſtellae, Sol iter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m me videbit:</hi> and vnder the head was a little marble cheſt, wherein a leaden box contained a parchment with this Prophecie: In thoſe daies many famous cities ſhall periſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, fearefull and terrible things ſhall come to paſſe and in <hi>Italy, Rome, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Tuskany,</hi> with my countrey of <hi>Hydrantum</hi> ſhall bee ſhaken in notable manner, and ſo ſhall <hi>Florence</hi> be affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21678:36"/> as expecting a reuenge, becauſe of her Apoſtate Duke, with a great deale more.</p>
                  <p>The formerly recited Saint <hi>Vincent</hi> in moſt of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings maketh as it were an agreement with the predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were ſound in the Abbot of <hi>Clunies</hi> Library <note place="margin">Abbot of Cluny.</note> written ſome 500. yeeres agoe againſt certaine <hi>Popes,</hi> that ſhall follow the ſteps of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and ſo drinke of the cup of the wrath of God, and whereas there are many and large prophecies attributed to Abbot <hi>Ioachim,</hi> yet they all tend to preſage the reformation of the Church, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of her obſtacles and enemies, that is, the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Colledge of <hi>Cardinals,</hi> or the obſeſſion and demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a Prophecy of <hi>Iohannes de rupe Sciſſa</hi> a <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſian</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</note> Friar: another of <hi>Theodoricus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Croatia:</hi> another in a booke intitled <hi>Stimulus diuinae contemplatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> another out of the Biſhops of <hi>Limoges</hi> Library in <hi>France:</hi> another of <hi>Laurenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s Miniatenſis,</hi> an Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of <hi>Naples,</hi> and many others from as many ſeuerall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, and countreys, and all tending to this end and purpoſe, that Religion muſt be reformed, according to the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> where the filthy garments are to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">Zachary 3.</note> away, and a crowne of pure gold to bee ſet vpon the Prieſts head. That Sathan ſhall be rebuked, that is to ſay, the hindrances of this good worke ſhall bee remoued: that this ſtrange exaltation of the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt bee abated, that their pompe and ſupremacy muſt bee diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that the very city ſhall be ſubiect to fire, and the countrey to inuaſion of enemies, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Shall tell you, how <hi>Hieronymus Sauanarola</hi> expounded <note place="margin">Sauanarola.</note> the reuelation of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to the people of <hi>Florence?</hi> He aſſured them, that religion muſt be reformed, that God would accuſe the Churches that were faultie, their trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries muſt be aboliſhed, their inuentions annihilated, &amp; that God would bring a great ſcourge vpon all <hi>Italie,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Rome:</hi> nor deſiſteth he ſo, but alledgeth the cauſe, and certaine motiues, why God was ſo extraordinarily offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21678:37"/> namely, the pollution of the Sanctuarie, the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Clergie, the ill gouernment of Prelates and Prieſts, the abuſes of Officers, and the pride of Biſhops and Cardinals, who will neither enter into heauen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (as Chriſt exprobrated the <hi>Phariſes)</hi> nor ſuffer others: which ſinnes muſt needs cry from the earth vnto heauen for vengeance, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It is wonderfull to relate that <hi>Panlus ſecundus Grebne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Grebnerus.</note> the <hi>German</hi> Aſtrologian ſhould ſo long agoe for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall foretell the vtter deſtruction of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> enlarging his inuectiues againſt idols, temples, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, defiled with mens inuentions, authoriſed by humane fancies, and adorned with gewgaw deuices, as if they were afraid to break the necke of policy by letting her looke vp to heauen, and therefore ſhe ſhould be troubled no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than the hangings, images, or painted walls of ſome melancholy Chappell. For the particular, hee progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated the deſtruction and diſſipation of the fleet in 88. the murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> the troubles of the King of <hi>Nauarre, Henry</hi> of <hi>Burbon,</hi> the preuailing of his armies, and the winning of the ſtrong towne of <hi>Groy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in <hi>Free ſland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But amongſt others, which I named before, you muſt <note place="margin">Abbot Ioachim.</note> needs harken vnto that famous and well reputed man <hi>Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimus</hi> the <hi>Italian</hi> Abbot of <hi>Flore</hi> in <hi>Calabria,</hi> who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheweth, that at laſt both <hi>Germans</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> ſhall ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deny the ſupremacie, becauſe of their monſtrous corruptions and iniquities. He alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, that as <hi>Salomon</hi> in his age fell to idolatrie, ſo ſhould <hi>Rome</hi> be moſt contaminated, when ſhe declined, and extend the violence of her filthineſſe, as the laſt act of her tragedie approached. He proceedeth yet further, that all Chriſtian Princes ſhall not onely forſake, but afflict her, yea a Prince ſmally reputed of ſhall correct the <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Harken I pray you to a little more: he reſembleth the Pope to <hi>Pharo</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and maketh a further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with her by the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> whore, and ſo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>death,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21678:37"/> that they ſhall all be laid in a bed of affliction, and ſcourged againe and againe with bleeding wounds for their wickedneſſe and abominations.</p>
                  <p>I could proceed with many others, but I did purpoſe onely an <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nchiridion,</hi> and therefore I will deſiſt from rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to a volume: yet I cannot ouerpaſſe thoſe bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues, and terrible preſages againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Robertus</hi> a <hi>Dominican</hi> Friar, who in diuers ſermons likens the <hi>Pope</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Friar Robert.</note> to an Idoll for adoration: to an <hi>Hidropick</hi> for preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: to a Beare for cruelty: to a ſerpent which in a viſion he ſaw in the palace of <hi>Laterane:</hi> to a blacke, dry, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted body: to an head of wood, which was to bee cut or broken off, and many other reſembiances tending all to this purpoſe, that in the end according to the time, which God hath kept ſecret in his owne boſome, <hi>Rome</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall not onely bee diſcouered to bee that man of ſinne, and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in the Scriptures, but receiue the reward of adultery euen the diuorce from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it bee ſo then, anſwer a Gods name you that muſt anſwer before the iudgement Throne of the Lambe, how comes this about, if the <hi>Papacy</hi> ſhall not come to ruine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe be deſtroied, ſceing <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, and that ſonne of perdition manifeſted, whom God will conſume with the breath of his noſtrils. If not ſo, ſhew, wherein either I haue gone beyond limitation, or my Authors haue failed in their computation, and I will anſwer both for them and my ſelfe, what is befitting to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, if God haue made your hearts pliable to a modeſt and humble impreſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Antichriſts puniſhment, and Romes deſtruction from holy women.</head>
                  <p>I Perceiue, For as in <hi>Peters</hi> viſion the ſheet was let downe, and propoſed vnto him full of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21678:38"/> cleane and vncleane beaſts: ſo in the Church of God, the women as well as the men haue not onely beene admitted, but admired for their ſanctity; yea as ftom the examples of Scripture, the Idolatrous nations aſſumed a patterne of imitation, falſifying <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering his ſonne <hi>Iſaac,</hi> to the inuention of ſlaughtering men to the Deuill: out of <hi>Samſons</hi> ſtory they haue iuſtified the life of <hi>Hercules:</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> Prieſthood, and <hi>Salomons</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they haue raiſed their ſuperſtitious adoration of idols, and Hecatombs of beaſts, with ſuch like: ſo hath the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in reſemblance of <hi>Miriam, Debora, Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Anna,</hi> and many others named Propheteſſes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women in Scripture, canonized Saints, of Nuns, and other deuotreſſes, whom they haue not onely reuerenced for their liues, but adored for their vertues, doctrine, and piety: amongſt whom I will only name you fiue, eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to memory by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelues, who ſhall furniſh this our preſent banquet of predictions with the dainties and accates of the beſt taſte to Gods true children, but of dangerous receit to the ſuperſtitious deuourer of nouelty, and new fangled deuices of men.</p>
                  <p>In the Propheticall viſions of Saint <hi>Hildegard a Nunne,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">St. Hildegard.</note> the ſecond booke of her <hi>Sciuias,</hi> there are diuers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lrs touching the deſolation of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deſtruction of the <hi>Pope,</hi> with intimation of the cauſe, as not onely for throwing the durt and filth of mens inuentions into the pure waters of the riuers of Gods Church, but for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing their liues in all abominations of impiety, and row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vp together into ſome ſtupendious heape the ſcattered ſnow of ſuperſtition, Relicks, Altar clothes, Pardons, Indulgences, and ſuch like trumperies, which will vaniſh and melt away as the ſnow, when the ſunny ſplendor of Gods word ſhineth hotly vpon them: for the Prophet tells vs, their beſt hypocriſie is but like the morning dew, <note place="margin">Hoſhea 6.</note> which is not ſeene within an houre or ſo after the Sunnes riſing.</p>
                  <p>There is another Prophecy of <hi>Mathilda,</hi> or as ſome <note place="margin">St. Mathilda.</note>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21678:38"/> haue it, <hi>Magdalena,</hi> a holy Saint, and religious woman, againſt <hi>Rome</hi> for her apoſtaſie, and the Cardinals for their aſſumpted greatneſſe and dangerous impietie: for which cauſe there ſhall be diuiſions in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces ſhall neuer be accorded in religion, till either the deſtruction or reformation of <hi>Rome</hi> be brought to paſſe. If you did reade the Originals, and would aduiſe vpon the congruent gradations of their writings, following as it were the order of Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie, you would either wonder how ſuch a ſpirit was infuſed in them, or that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not ſince ſuppreſſed or aboliſhed their inuectiues. But (as I ſaid) God doth worke by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret meanes and ſtrange inſtruments, and when he hath either a mercy or a iudgement to execute, <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſhall be his anointed, <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> his ſeruant, and very wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tyrants and infidels his hammer to bruiſe the ſtones in peeces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> was alſo a Nunne and Propheteſſe, and <note place="margin">S. Elizabeth.</note> hath her Viſions too: ſo that in the ſecond booke you ſhall finde how ſhe expoſtulateth the matter with the corrupt Clergie, why they ſhould preach erronious doctrine, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the ſacred Scriptures, continue in abomination of life, maintaine the abſurdities of Traditions, &amp;c. Then ſhe exprobrateth the Biſhops for their ſchiſmaticall filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, chargeth the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with deadneſſe and errour, reproueth the Popes of ſimonie and vnheard of vitiouſneſſe, and laſt of all ſhe commeth vnto iudgement, and threatneth them all with vtter deuaſtation and ruine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Bridget</hi> had alſo her reuelations; ſhe was a holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <note place="margin">S. Bridget.</note> religious widow, and princeſſe of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rice</hi> in <hi>Sweth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> they are wonderfull both for the number and the large approbation of many learned and iudicious Papiſts, who all commend her ſanctimonious life, and confirme he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpirituall raptures. In one place ſhe challengeth the Pope and corrupt Clergie of <hi>Rome,</hi> of many enormities, denouncing Gods iudgement againſt them. In another ſhe would haue the Scriptures to be read in the mother
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21678:39"/> tongue. In a third ſhe curſeth the ſelling of ſpirituall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and threatneth a woe, if the cuſtome be not abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated and aboliſhed. In a fourth ſhe is much exafperated againſt <hi>Rome</hi> for many aberrations, eſpecially <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>weruing from her primitiue excellencie. In a fift ſhe enlarging her ſelfe, maketh a Catalogue of infinite number of vices and errors to which <hi>Rome</hi> was ſubiected. In a ſixth ſhe inciteth the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to the calling of a Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and bringing <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>Foro publico</hi> by accuſation. In a ſeuenth ſhee inueigheth againſt the fornication of Prieſts, proteſting it were better to marry, nay warranting that the prohibition of marriage was vtterly vnlawfull. In another ſhe thus preſageth, and ratifies it with a forcible oath, that the reformation of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt begin with the ſword, and ſo ſeuen plagues ſhall fall vpon her, as it was ſpoken vnto <hi>Iſrael.</hi> In a ninth ſhe ſheweth the difference betweene Chriſts and the Popes Church, or if you will, the Popes Court, enlarging the particulars by diuers cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and demonſtratiue reaſons. In a tenth ſhe conteſteth againſt that impious opinion of mens merits in matter of ſaluation, as a very poiſon to infect the heart of true religion, and open a gap to let in a world of abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. In another ſhe wonders how that Purgatorie came into mens minds, more than that it was a deuice of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to make a mint for the ſelling of ſoules, or at the beſt to coine money to fill the Popes treaſurie. In the laſt place ſhe aſſureth them that God will raiſe vp better vine-dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers in his vineyard, than were in her time, or elſe leaue it deſolate to the foxes, who ſhall deſtroy it for euer. What would ſhe ſay then if ſhe liued in theſe dayes, and were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the new ſect of Ieſuites, the Popes Ianiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the worlds Incendiaries; with the doctrine of equiuocation and mentall reſeruation; with that atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call poſition of <hi>Fidesnon eſt ſeruanda haereticis</hi> and all thoſe damnable diſpenſations with murders, depoſitions of Princes, inceſts, whoredomes, and ſuch like?</p>
                  <p>There is neuer a Papiſt in the world but honoureth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21678:39"/> 
                     <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Sienna</hi> for a Saint, and religious woman. <note place="margin">S. Katherine.</note> Now, if he will but beleeue her writings, as he reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth her perſon, and exalteth her memorie, let him giue eare to her Prophecies. She beginneth very ſanctimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with a praier for the reformation of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſhe proceedeth effectually to lay open the enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſame: ſhe continueth moſt ſeriouſly in diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the miſchiefes they haue done to the poore afflicted ſoules of Chriſtendome; and ſhe concludeth very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ily, that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall incurre tribulation, and be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroied for her abominable life and impoſturing deceit: That the Pope ſhall be diſrobed, and loſe his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Crowne, yea be bereaued of all his pompe and glory, and that the Cardinals ſhall caſt off their ſcarlet gownes, and run to hide themſelues, if they knew where: but death and deſolation ſhall follow them into their cloſets, and their very Idols and Images ſhall make a fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, ſo that their louers and friends ſhall crie out, <hi>Heu cadit in quenquam tantum ſcelus, tanta iniquitas!</hi> yea their very enemies ſhall clap their hands for joy to ſee their filthineſſe laied open to the hiſſing of the paſſengers.</p>
                  <p>If this be thus, then anſwer a Gods name, you that muſt anſwer before the iudgement throne of the Lambe, how comes this about, if the Papacie ſhall not come to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtroied, ſeeing Antichriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, and that ſonne of perdition manifeſted, whom God will conſume with the breath of his noſtrils. If not ſo, ſhew wherein I haue gone beyond limitation, or my Authors failed in their account, and I will anſwer both for them and my ſelfe, what is befitting ſatisfaction, if God haue made your hearts pliable to an humble and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt impreſſion. And thus much for Antichriſts puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I finde the ſubſtance of all that hath beene ſaid in one continued diſcourſe vpon the eleuenth Chap. of the fourth booke of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> I will enlarge the ſame. For the Papiſts themſelues allow the Apocrypha, as authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21678:40"/> as Canonicall Scripture, wee onely maintaine, that though it be not Canonicall Scripture, yet our learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines attribute to theſe Apocryphall writings the next place to the Canonicall Scripture: and ſo you ſhall not only haue the Originall <hi>verbatim,</hi> but a true and ſtrange Paraphraſe, or illuſtration approued by the beſt authoritie.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>ESDRAS 2. Chap. 11.</bibl>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>THen ſaw I a dreame, and behold there came vp from the ſea an Eagle which had twelue feathered wings and three heads.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 <hi>And I ſaw, and behold ſhee ſpred her wings ouer all the earth, and all the windes of the aire blew on her, and were gathered together.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 <hi>And I beheld, and out of her feathers there grew other contrarie feathers, and they became little feathers and ſmall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 <hi>But her heads were at reſt, the head in the midſt was greater than the other; yet reſted it with the reſidue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 <hi>Moreouer, I beheld, and loe, the Eagle flew with her feathers, and reigned vpon the earth, and ouer them that dwelt therein.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 <hi>And I ſaw, that all things vnder Heauen were ſubiect vnto her, and no man ſpake againſt her, no not one creature vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>And I beheld, and loe the Eagle roſe vpon her tallons, and ſpake to her feathers ſaying,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8 <hi>Watch not all at once, ſleepe euerie one in his owne place, and watch by courſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">9 <hi>But let the heads be preſerued for the laſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10 <hi>And I beheld, and loe the voice went not out of her heads, but from the midſt of her bodie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11 <hi>And I numbred her contrarie feathers, and behold, there were eight of them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">12 <hi>And I looked, and behold on the right ſide there aroſe one feather and reigned ouer all the earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="13">13 <hi>And ſo it was that when it reigned, the end of it</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21678:40"/> 
                        <hi>came, and the place thereof appeared no more, ſo the next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſtood vp, and reigned, and had a great time.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="14">14 <hi>And it happened that when it reigned, the end of it came alſo, like as the firſt, ſo that it appeared no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="15">15 <hi>Then came there a vcice vnto it and ſaid,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="16">16 <hi>Heare thou that haſt borne rule ouer the earth ſo long, this I ſay vnto thee, before thou beginneſt to appeare no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="17">17 <hi>There ſhall none after thee attaine vnto thy time, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto the halfe thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="18">18 <hi>Then aroſe the third, and reigned as the others before, and appeared no more alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="19">19 <hi>So went it with all the reſidue one after another, as that euery one reigned, and then appeared no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="20">20 <hi>Then I beheld and loe in proceſſe of time the feathers, that followed, ſtood vp on the right ſide, that they might rule alſo, and ſome of them ruled, but within a while they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="21">21 <hi>For ſome of them were ſet vp, but ruled not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="22">22 <hi>After this I looked, and behold the 12. feathers appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no more, nor the two little feathers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="23">23 <hi>And there was no more vpon the Eagles body but three heads that reſted and ſix little wings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="24">24 <hi>Then ſaw I alſo, that two little feathers diuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the ſix, and remained vnder the head, that was vpon the right ſide, for the foure continued in their place.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="25">25 <hi>And I beheld and loe, the feathers, that were vnder the wing, thought to ſet vp themſelues, and to haue the rule.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="26">26 <hi>And I beheld, and loe, there was one ſet vp, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it appeared no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="27">27 <hi>And the ſecond was ſooner away than the firſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="28">28 <hi>And I beheld, and loe the two that remained thought alſo in themſelues to reigne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="29">29 <hi>And when they ſo thought, behold there awaked one of the heads that were at reſt, namely it that was in the midſt, for that was greater than the two other heads.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="30">30 <hi>And then I ſaw that the two other heads were ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="31">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21678:41"/>31 <hi>And behold the head was turned with them, that were with it, and did eat vp the two feathers vnder the wing, that would haue reigned.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="32">32 <hi>But this head put the whole earth in feare, and bare rule in it ouer all thoſe that dwelt vpon the earth, with much oppreſſion, and it had the gouernance of the world, more than all the wings that had beene.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="33">33 <hi>And after this I beheld, and loe, the head that was in the midſt ſuddenly appeared no more, like as the wings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="34">34 <hi>But there remained the two heads, which alſo in like ſort ruled vpon the earth, and ouer thoſe that dwelt therein.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="35">35 <hi>And I beheld, and loe, the head vpon the right ſide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured it that was vpon the left ſide.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="36">36 <hi>Then I heard a voice which ſaid vnto me, looke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and conſider the thing that thou ſeeſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="37">37 <hi>And I beheld, and loe as it were a roaring Lion cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the wood, and I ſaw that he ſent out a mans voice vnto the Eagle and ſaid,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="38">38 <hi>Heare thou: I will talke with thee, and the higheſt ſhall ſay vnto thee,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="39">39 <hi>Art not thou it that remaineſt of the foure beaſts, whom I made to reigne in my world, that the end of their times might come through them?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="40">40 <hi>And the fourth came, and ouercame all the beaſts that were paſt, and had power ouer the world with great fearefulneſſe, and ouer the whole compaſſe of the earth with much wicked oppreſſion, and ſo long time dwelt he vpon the earth with deceit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="41">41 <hi>For the earth haſt thou not iudged with truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="42">42 <hi>For thou haſt afflicted the meeke, thou haſt burt the peaceable, thou haſt loued liers, and deſtroied the dwellings of them that brought forth fruit, and haſt caſt downe the walls of ſuch as did thee no harme.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="43">43 <hi>Therefore is thy wrongfull dealing come vp vnto the higheſt, and thy pride vnto the mighty.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="44">44 <hi>The higheſt alſo hath looked vpon the proud times, and behold they are ended, and his abominations are fulfilled.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="45">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21678:41"/>45 <hi>And therefere appeare no more thou Eagle, nor thy horrible wings, nor thy wicked feathers, nor thy malicious heads, nor thy hurtfull clawes, nor all thy vaine body.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="46">46 <hi>That all the earth may be refreſhed, and may returne being deliuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d from thy violence, and that ſhe may hope for the iudgement and mercy of him that made her.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>If you reade alſo the next chapter, you may finde how <hi>Eſdras</hi> expounded this viſion: but becauſe I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed a more plenary ſatisfaction, I apply my ſelfe to the ſame purpoſe, and thus continue the diſcourſe. In the daies of <hi>Darius</hi> king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſome 400. yeeres before <hi>lulins Caeſar</hi> aduanced the ſtandard of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the preſentation of a <hi>ſable Eagle</hi> diſplaied in a golden field, as the firſt <hi>Emperor</hi> after Kings, <hi>Conſuls</hi> and <hi>Dictators</hi> this viſion came to <hi>Eſdras,</hi> and containeth the beginning, continuance, and diſſolution of the <hi>Empire</hi> and ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeene by the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> ſome few yeeres before: wherein twelue only <hi>Emperors</hi> are perſonated for their extended power like wings ouer the world, and for their greatneſſe and celſitude of birth, like beaſts with iron teeth &amp; nailes of braſſe, the number as a full iury to include the reſt, and their nobleneſſe farre exceeding other infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, as deſcended from the families of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lij, Seruij, Saluij, Flauij, &amp;c.</hi> Wheras all others were but compoſed of meane originalls, or contrary nations, and no natiue <hi>Romans.</hi> By her three heads are meant three kingdomes, which muſt behold the pride of <hi>Rome,</hi> when her wings and feathers ſhall faile. By the winds are vnderſtood her proſperity, and large extenſion of dominion, as limiting her territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from <hi>Ganges</hi> to <hi>Gades,</hi> and from the <hi>Scythian</hi> ſea to <hi>Cape bona eſperanza.</hi> By the contrary feathers you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand certaine Kings and Princes that oppoſed this tranſcendent mightineſſe of <hi>Rome:</hi> but their purpoſes were fruſtrated, and for the time they preuailed not, till at laſt one was mightier than the reſt, yet all reſted for a time: for they were as embrions vnbroughtforth till this great city in her vnlimited pompe and pride, with her Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21678:42"/> and Legions might ſubiugate the neighbour nations, and inſult ouer the beſt of the earth. By the ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her clawes, &amp;c. the Prieſts obſerued, that <hi>Rome</hi> in her tranſcendency did nothing without counſell and good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, wherby her <hi>Emperors</hi> kept the ſoueraignty with great caution, and policy, and obtained a renoune beyond all ciries and kings in the Vniuerſe. Now you muſt conſider, that what <hi>Eſdras</hi> perſonateth by an Eagle, the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> deſigneth vnder the forme of a ten-horned beaſt, <note place="margin">Daniel 7.</note> berokening diuers Emperors &amp; Kings, whoſe vnreſiſtable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orces ſhould affright the world with ambition, tyranny, and couetouſneſſe, and whereas he proceedeth with a race and ſucceſſion of gouernors differing in ſhape and forme from their predeceſſors, but gouerning with blaſpheming the moſt High, ſitting in the Temple, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrannizing ouer the third part of the world, and continuingin greater rages and cruelty againſt the inhabitants of the Prouinces, than the reſt; what is it any other than after the <hi>Emperors</hi> that &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, the <hi>Popes</hi> ſhall challenge a ſupremacy and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue power ouer inferiour kings, and by wonderfull ſubtilty, that is, the ſhadow of piety, religion, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious life, preuaile in elation of heart, and power of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty, and therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>and he ſhall bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to the firſt:</hi> yet ſtill muſt <hi>Rome</hi> be called <hi>Triumphanta</hi> and <hi>Santa:</hi> ſo that when the Eagle ſaw her feathers pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and that <hi>Senat us populuſque Romanus</hi> could doe no good, nor <hi>Imperium Romanum</hi> preuaile by forcible intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhe fearing ſome incurable diſeaſe to grow vpon her, and that ſhee muſt needs ſaint in her weakneſſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, ſet a new Loome on worke of policy, lies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, yea Magicke, and Witchcraft, and ſo vnder the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name of <hi>Eccleſia Dei Romae,</hi> once againe aduanced her ſtandard of honour and reputation, and became as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in her ſpirituall gouernment, as euer ſhee was in the warlike dilacerations of her Prouinces.</p>
                  <p>But the ſtory followes in the numbring the Eagles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <note place="margin">Verſe 11.</note> feathers, that is to ſay, that after <hi>Rome</hi> had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaid
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21678:42"/> the world, and her glorious <hi>Emperors</hi> with <hi>Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> pride, aduanced themſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s as high as the Sunne: there ſhould diuers attempts be made by forraine nations, and dangerous Princes to diſmantell her of her Imperiall robes, and vnplume her of her diuerſity of colours, and theſe were compriſed vnder the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mber of eight. 1. The Weſt <hi>Gothes</hi> commanded by <hi>Alaricus.</hi> 2. the <hi>Huns</hi> by <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tala.</hi> 3. the <hi>Vandals</hi> by <hi>Genſcricus.</hi> 4. the remainder of them by <hi>Odoacer.</hi> 5. the Eaſt <hi>Gothes</hi> by <hi>Thecdorick.</hi> 6. the reſt by <hi>Totila.</hi> 7. The <hi>Lombards</hi> or <hi>Longobardi</hi> by <hi>Albonius.</hi> 8. and the laſt by an inteſtine ſedition and domeſticke conſpiracy, which infeſted as much or more, than all the reſt: I could adde as enemies, the <hi>Radaguiſe, Alani</hi> or <hi>Almans, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonians</hi> vnder <hi>Gundibald, Hungars, Saracens,</hi> and diuers other, but the former were thoſe principall incendiaries, that ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire indeed, and by manifeſt repugnancy pulled her walles to rubbiſh, which laſted all the time of her oſtentation with the tearme of <hi>Imperium crbis terrae,</hi> but when it came to the counterchange of <hi>Mater Eccleſia,</hi> then did theſe Princes likewiſe inueſt her with new robes of ſtate and magnificence, and were content to take the golden cup from the Strumpets hands, and carowſe the dregs of abomination, &amp; thus is the ſtory of <hi>Rome</hi> epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed euen to this houre; but becauſe the Prophecie goes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I will follow in the ſtrength I haue, &amp; begin againe.</p>
                  <p>One feather aroſe on the right ſide, and reigned, ſaith the <note place="margin">verſe 12.</note> text. In thoſe daies the great ones repined at the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Conſuls, and the inſcription of <hi>Senatus populuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Romanus,</hi> whereupon diuers families attempted the ſole iuriſdiction: as the <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ehj, Marius, Scilla, Cateline,</hi> all as noble and as well borne as <hi>Iulins;</hi> but none roſe on the right ſide but he, and although it coſt him his life in the enterpriſe, as betraied by his deareſt friends, who ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſing the liberty of their countrey before the ambition of an intruder, taught him a new leſſon, that in truſt was treaſon, and there is no confidence in worldly proſperity, but time will haue her viciſſitude: but for all this, out of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21678:43"/> death ſprung the life of imperiouſneſſe, for after <hi>Octauius, Anthony,</hi> and <hi>Lepidus</hi> had reuenged his death, and plaied the wanton <hi>Triumuiri</hi> with the greatneſſe and potency of gouernment, <hi>Octauius</hi> ſhouldred away the reſt, and for his happy determination of buſineſſe, and proſperous ſucceſſe in all affaires, reigned forty foure yeeres alone as <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> then followed <hi>Tiber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us, Caius, Caligula, Claudius, Nero, Galba, Otho, Vitellius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian, Titus, Domitian,</hi> and theſe are the feathers and wings of the Eagle principally named in this prophecie.</p>
                  <p>Now ſaith the Text, there were other feathers, but they <note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> put not themſelues forth with that ſtrength, nor made ſo glorious a ſhew as the former: that is, there were other Emperours and Gouernours, but they were neither ſo mighty in gouernment nor ſo illuſtred in birth: ſuch as <hi>Nerua, Adrian, Anthonius, Marius, Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dus, Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nax, Iulian, Seuerus, Caracalla, Macrinus, Heliogabalus, Alexander, Maximinus,</hi> with others to the 3. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and ſo by degrees as it is in Philoſophie, <hi>corrupti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vnius generatio alterius,</hi> the Empire decaying, the papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy had roome in <hi>Rome</hi> for a new progreſſion.</p>
                  <p>All this while you muſt conſider, there were others which were oppoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es and innouators, but no gouernors, and theſe, ſaith the text, were ſet vp, but not ruled: ſuch as <hi>Vindex, Piſcenius niger, Albinus, Diadumenas, Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imus, Balbinus, 30. Tyranni, Firmus, Saturninus, Bonoſus, Proculus, Aper, Eugenius, Quintillus, Ruffinus, Conſtantinus,</hi> not ſurnamed <hi>Magnus, Heraclianus,</hi> and others, who all ſerued to no other end, but as inſtruments for the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to hew downe the marble pillers of this Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Rome,</hi> and afterward to raiſe a new fabricke of ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious admiration, by a farre more vnnaturall gouernment of Church-men, I call it vnnaturall, becauſe the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder the ſanctified titles of <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars to the Lambe, and fathers of the Church of God, not onely deceiued the world, but excelled the proudeſt Emperors, when their ſinnes came to ouerflowing, in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21678:43"/> State, Maieſtie, Pompe, couetouſneſſe, tyranny, and all other impieties diſcouered in Scripture.</p>
                  <p>But the Prophet goes forward with the Empires diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that is to ſay, with the whole narration of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Nations that infeſted <hi>Italy,</hi> beginning with <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi> who ſet himſelfe vp in the 19. yeere of <hi>Honorius,</hi> conquering <hi>Latium, Campania, Apulia, Lucania, Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria,</hi> proceeding with <hi>Attila,</hi> who in the 27. of the 3. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>410</label> 
                     <hi>Valentinian</hi> deſtroi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Aquileia, Verona, Mantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, Cremona, Brixia, Coneordia,</hi> with the new territory of <hi>Venice,</hi> and ending with <hi>Genſerick, Od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acer, Totila,</hi> the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and the inteſtine faction: and theſe are the two heads and <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> ſix wings: now you muſt conſider, that in this fearefull time, the proud <hi>Attila</hi> did fell the city of <hi>Rome</hi> to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Leo,</hi> as ſome report, and ſo was contented to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <hi>Italy,</hi> by which occaſion the Popes became Maſters of this great City, and in proceſſe of time wrought out their ſupremacy, not onely ouer <hi>Italy,</hi> but ouer <hi>Europe:</hi> For as theſe Tyrants vexed one another, and the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors which followed were ſubiect to extirpation, namely <hi>Valentinian, Maximus, Anitus, Maiorianus, Seuerus, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themias, Olibrius, Glycerius, lxlius, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pos, Momil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> the Popes raiſed their ſtructures out of their ruines, and the rubbiſh of the Empire ſerued to aduance the fabricke of the Papacy: Thus the Eagles diſplaid wings were ſpread in the time of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and broken and ſpoiled in the daies of <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> who was that <hi>Momil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us</hi> the laſt named, and ſo the prophecy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth to the 29. verſe, with the varietie of the warres, troubles, and gouernment, of all the contrary feathers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before, to the time of the inteſtine ſedition, which had pretence of renuing the ſtile of <hi>Senatus populuſque Romanus:</hi> but now the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> tampers for his ſupremacy, and inueſteth <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and this is that which <hi>Eſdras</hi> meaneth, by the awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of one of the three heads, that were at reſt: for the <note place="margin">Verſ. 29. 801</note> three heads perſonate <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> who
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21678:44"/> ſhall according to the interpretation of this Viſion, ſtill by one meanes or other maintaine the dignity of the Popedome, though all the reſt of the Kings and Princes of Europe forſake it, till vtter deſtruction come indeed, and they manifeſtly behold, that God will c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt this ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet in a bed of affliction, that is to ſay, that although <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry</hi> and the profeſſion of the Romiſh Religion ſhall not be vtterly extinguiſhed, till the Church be triumphant in heauen, yet ſhall the glory of <hi>Rome,</hi> yea of the Pope and his Cardinalls ſuffer diminution, if not vtter d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as ſhall be manifeſted in due place, and orderly demonſtration.</p>
                  <p>But firſt you muſt note, how the Prophet proceeds: the <note place="margin">verſe 31.</note> middle head did eat vp the wings, which is meant by the ſword of <hi>Carclus magnus,</hi> who at the Popes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand came into <hi>Italy</hi> and tooke <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>derius</hi> priſoner, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him captiue into <hi>France;</hi> after this <hi>Cono</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour falls out with <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oiected to diſlocate the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> as intimating, that their pride and tyranny would grow vlcerous, and to a <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gren</hi> in the body of Europes gouernment: whereupon the people were not only incenſed againſt their Biſhop, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted a new alteration, by <hi>Senators</hi> and <hi>Conſuls,</hi> had not the <hi>French</hi> laid a cooling card for this proceeding, and eſtabliſhed the Pope in his ſupreme eminency: yet all is not quiet; for ſome 150. yeeres after <hi>Alberick</hi> and <hi>Octauian</hi> his ſonne conteſted anew with the ambitious Prelates, and once againe aduanced another gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Rome:</hi> but ſee how the <hi>Pope</hi> thriues according to the prophecie: <hi>Otho</hi> the great comes in his aſſiſtance, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the Conſull, hangeth the Tribunes, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the <hi>Praefectus Vrbis</hi> naked on an Aſſe, and ſo hee is crowned, and with great deriſion thruſt into priſon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ormented to death: but within ſeuen yeeres new vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares began by the tumul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uary incitation of <hi>Lancius,</hi> had not <hi>Otho</hi> the ſecond at a ſupper in the <hi>Vatican</hi> ſtrucke off all their heads. Laſt of all, <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt, with the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1136</label>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21678:44"/> bloud and wounds of 2000. men eſtabliſhed the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in greater glory, and euer ſince according to this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie and diſcouery, they haue continued ſecure by the meanes of theſe heads in all impiety and abomination: but the Prophecy leaues them not ſo, for after all this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification of glory and greatneſſe, with the manner of their riſing, and inſolent tumors, he falles to their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vtter confuſion.</p>
                  <p>This laſteth from the 36, verſe to the end, wherein you may obſerue, that the breath of God like a Lion of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſhall teare this Eagle in peeces, and as you haue heard in the execution of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> whole armies of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and denunciations of vengeance ſhall be further mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred againſt <hi>Rome</hi> from ſo ſupreme a iudicature, that no humane potency ſhall reuerſe the doome, or be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale the ſentence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THe concluſion then of all theſe things may be thus, that if God out of his palace of power and mightineſſe, or ſtore-houſe of prouidence and mercy, hath from time to time expoſed his ſecrets openly, whereby his Saints and poore afflicted children haue not only beene comforted in their diſtreſſe, but prepared againſt following miſchiefes: If according to the wantonneſſe of times, and growth of impietie, he hath gone about to ſtop the torrent and raging inundation of wickedneſſe, and by many predictions fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the ruine of the kingdome of Sathan, and enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the bounds of his Church: If he hath gone yet further to follow obſtinate men and refractarie delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, euen at the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les, with ſignes and wonders from heauen, either to diuert the outragious from their immani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or ſupport the lowly in their humiliation: Let not vs paſſe them ouer, as things vnremarkable, or be affrighted as terrors of too great vengeance: and if it fall not within our reach to make cleane euery corruption, yet as neere as we can, to wipe away the filthineſſe, and waſh off the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of groſſe and fearfull ſinnes. Thus ſhall the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ioyes to come ſeaſon our preſent ſorrowes, &amp; the acknowledging of Gods attributes aſſure vs, that he is faithfull, which hath promiſed, and ſo will performe the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21678:45"/> oath he ſware vnto our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed for euer.</p>
               <p>Againe, if it hath pleaſed the ſame God to terrifie the world with the rumors of warre, and thundrings of hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o weaken and abate the power of mightie monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, to ſtrike <hi>Daniels</hi> image with a ſtone from heauen to peeces, to put a hooke in the noſtrils of <hi>Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athan</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>moth,</hi> to turne about the wheeles of the chariot of greatneſſe. O conſider this ye that haue forgot God, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt he teare you in peeces in his wrath: &amp; remember this, ye that loue God, leſt ye abuſe his mercy ouer-preſumptuouſly.</p>
               <p>But of all, and exceeding all; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in this latter age of the world he hath reuealed vnto vs the true hiſtorie of his Church; That the Dragon ſhall watch the woman in the wilde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe to deuoure her childe; That in the Primitiue Church was the true pattern of wholſome words; That ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell from thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puritie, &amp; was polluted with the filth of mens Traditions, whoſe daring hands out of wantonneſſe, caſe, gurrm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dice, ambicion, auarice, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie, and impoſturing deceit, threw dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into her cleane ſtreame, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner dammed vp the ſpring of vndeniable veritie; That all this was done by Antichriſt and his adherents; That this Antichriſt is now fully diſcouered, not to perſonate one man, nor be a ſtranger in Gods houſe, but to ſit in the Temple of God, and the Church, and to be the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſtrumpet of <hi>Babylon</hi> in the Scriptures, the beaſt with ſeuen heads and ten hornes in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> the man of ſinne in <hi>Timothie, Lucifer</hi> in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the ſpirit of error in the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> with all the reſt, as you haue heard; That notwithſtanding this diſcouerie, he hath vſurped the authoritie of Princes, tyrannized ouer Kings, affrighted ignorant ſoules, captiued c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dulous perſons, and enriched his purſe, to the augmentation of worldly glory; That therefore God hath arraigned him, and by ſeuerall indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments condemned, and that his puniſhment and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cution followed, whereby this defiled ſtrumpet ſhall be diuorced from her ſpouſe, caſt in a bed of affliction, demo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed, and her ſtructures pulled to peeces, ſet on fire, to the wonder of the world, and the terror of all ſeduced people.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
